<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An acte of the relief graunted to the Kinges Maiestie by the Lordes and commons.</title>
            <title>Laws, etc.</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1549</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 114 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B13269</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 9427.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide Harl.7615[14]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99892832</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99892832</idno>
            <idno type="VID">189036</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B13269)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 189036)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C14:3[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An acte of the relief graunted to the Kinges Maiestie by the Lordes and commons.</title>
                  <title>Laws, etc.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
                  <author>Edward VI, King of England, 1537-1553.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>xvii [i.e. 34], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted in the house of Richard Grafton, printer to the Kynges Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1549].</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Historiated initial.</note>
                  <note>Pages numbered on recto only.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from STC; printer's information from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes in ms.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Includes Harleian mss. 7615 leaves 14-31.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Edward VI, 1547-1553 --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="act">
            <pb facs="tcp:189036:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN ACTE OF THE RELIEF GRAVNTED TO THE KINGES MAIESTIE by the Lordes and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hyleſt we the kynges maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties faythfull louing and obedient ſubiectes, the lordes &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in this preſent parliament do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyder the preſent ſtate of the worlde, what great troubles be in all places, what enemies both his maieſtie and this his realme hath and is lyke to haue, and that their malice and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred is bent, partly to dyminiſhe his graces maieſtie &amp; the honour of this his Realme, partly to ſpoile the ſame of the iuſt, true, &amp; auncient enheritaunce, right, and title, that his high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; his moſt noble progenitours kinges of this Realme of England haue alwayes had to the Realme of Scotland, being a member and part of his kingdome and dominion: and chieflye for that we of late ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing abandoned the aucthoritie of the Byſhop of Rome and his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked doctrine, haue and do adhere to Chriſte and his moſt holy word, as becometh all chriſtians to do, that mean to be no leſſe in dede, then they profeſſe in name: Whyleſt we alſo conſyder, that his grace, and we his faithful and obedient ſubiectes be but one body politique, his highnes the head and we the members, and that no good or felicitie can come to the one, but the other ſhalbe partaker therof, and that no hurt or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſytie can happen to the one where with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſhall not alſo be gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid: Whyleſt alſo we conſyder the practyſes and policies of other prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and potentates, what great preparations, they make both of men and alſo of other furniture for the warres, and what great treaſure thei of late haue leuied and gathered of their ſubiectes: we perceyuing that all the kynges maieſties procedings holye tend to the aduauncement of the true glorie of God, the maintenaunce of the maieſtie of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall crowne of this Realme, and the defence and ſauitee of vs &amp; this his realme, fully minded to cleaue &amp; ſtick to God &amp; his moſt holy word, vtterlie determined to mainteyne his graces honour and all ſuch righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and titles as be annexed to his Imperiall croune, preſt and redie, to defende our ſelfes &amp; this his realme &amp; our countrie: and fynally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to leaue father, mother, brethren, ſyſtren, wyfes, chyldren, landes, goodes, yea, and this mortal life alſo, rather then we would deny Chriſt and forſake his worde, whiche is the lyuelye foode of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſoule, rather then we would ſuffer his royall maieſtie, to be in any part diminiſhed, rather then we would conſent, that the Imperial crowne of this realme ſhould be depriued of any honour, tytle, ryght or intereſt therunto belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng:
<pb facs="tcp:189036:2"/> &amp; fynally rather then any forien powre, ſhould do vs or our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie any hurt or iniurye, haue thought it good to prepare and make not only our perſones redie for the warres, hauing a full affyaunce &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fydence in God, that as he alwaies hath lent victorie to ſuche as profeſſed him &amp; put their hole truſt in him: albeit they were but verye few and that very feble in mans ſight, in reſpect of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> multitude &amp; force of their enemies: ſo he now wyll haue ſpeciall regarde &amp; eye to this litle realme, and vs his poore ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes &amp; litle flocke, taking to his charge and defence our litle ſhephard, tyll yeares &amp; ſtrength make him better able to vicket with his enemies, &amp; that therfore he with vs &amp; for vs wyl deuiſe to withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, reſiſt, &amp; ſubdue the force and puiſſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of our ſtoute foes, no more ours then his, at the leaſt, ours for his cauſe: but alſo to make among vs a maſſe of money, to relief &amp; mainteine the great &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtymable charges that our moſt graciouſe ſoueraigne lorde hath &amp; dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie doth ſuſteine, a thing much vnable to ſerue any pece of his preſent neceſſities, if his grace did meane to ſpare any part of his own treaſure, beſeching his grace, not to caſt his eyes, vpon the ſmalnes of this our ſymple preſent, but to laye by it our good wylles, whiche we make the chiefeſt part of our relief, it faithfully promyſyng, al the reſt to be redy, when peryll or enemy ſhall declare this not to ſuffyce. Firſt we his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſaid ſubiectes do by the aucthoritie of this preſent parliament frely and franckelie geue and graunt vnto his moſt royall maieſtie a relief, to continue by the ſpace of .iij. yeres to be rated, taxed, leuied and gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of euery parſon of what eſtate or degree he be, according to the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of this acte after the rate and in maner and fourme followyng, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, aſwel of al &amp; euery perſon as is or hereafter ſhalbe his graces natural ſubiectes, as of al &amp; euery fraternitie, guilde, corporatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, miſtery brotherhed, companye and cominaltye corporat or not corporat within this realme of England, wales and other the kynges dominions being worth ten pondes in money, Coyne, plate, ſtocke of marchandiſe, corne grayne, ſhepe, beaſtes, cattals or other goodes mouable, aſwell within this realme as without, and of all ſuche ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes of money as to hym or them is or ſhalbe owing, wherof he or they truſt in their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcientes ſuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to be payed: yerely twelue pence of euery pound. And of euery alien or ſtraunger borne out of the kinges obeyſaunce aſwell denyſen as not denyſen inhabityng or reſyaunt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in this realme or any other y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinges dominions beyng worth ten poundes in money, coyne, plate, ſtocke of marchandiſe, corne, grayne, ſhepe, beaſtes, cattals, or other goodes mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uable, aſwell within this realme as without, and of al ſuche ſommes of money as to him is or ſhalbe owing, wherof he truſteth in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience to be ſuerly payed: yerely two ſhyllynges of euery pound. And of euery alyen or ſtraunger borne out of the kinges obeyſaunce aſwell denyſen as not denyſen inhabiting or reſyaunt within this realme or any other the kynges dominions, beyng worth twenty ſhyllynges and vnder ten poundes in money, coyne, plate, ſttocke of merchaundiſe, corne, grayne,
<pb n="ij" facs="tcp:189036:2" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſhepe, beaſtes, cattell, or other goodes mouable, aſwel within this real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me as without, and of al ſuch ſommes of money as to him is or ſhalbe owing, wherof he truſteth in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience to be ſuerly paid, yerely twelf pence of euery pound. Except &amp; out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> premyſſes deducted ſuche ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of money as any perſon or perſones before chargeable owe and in his or their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce truly minde to paie. And excepted alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apparel of ſuch parſons their wifes &amp; childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> belongi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to their awne bodies, ſaui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g iewels, gold, ſyluer, ſtone &amp; perle. Excepted alſo alwayes from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> charge, aſſeſſement &amp; payment of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid relief, all money, goodes &amp; cattalles of orphanes bequethed or lefte vnto them by their parentes or other their frendes deceaſſyd. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all plate, coyne, Iewels, goodes, debtes, &amp; cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, perſonalles, being in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rule &amp; cuſtodie of any perſon or perſones to the vſe of any corporatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, fraternitie, guild, miſterie, brotherhod, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye or any cominaltie being corporat, or not corporat, be &amp; ſhalbe rated, ſet, &amp; charged by reaſon of this acte, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> value certefied by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tours of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> certificat, to be ſworne, of euery pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in goodes, &amp; debtes as is abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſaid. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſommes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are before reherſed, ſet &amp; taxed, to be leuied, &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhall haue ſuch goodes in cuſtodie, as is before reherſed. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame parſon, or parſones, &amp; bodye corporate by the aucthorite of this acte, ſhalbe diſcharged againſt him or them, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhal or ought to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame at the time of the paiment or delyuerie therof, or at his other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe departure from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cuſtodie or poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. Except &amp; alwaies forpryſed from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> charge &amp; aſſeſſement of this relief, all goodes, cattals, Iewels, &amp; orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of churches &amp; chapelles, ordeined, &amp; vſed in chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches or chappelles, for diuine ſeruice therin to be celebrated. Alſo we y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinges maieſties ſubiectes do geue, &amp; graunt to his highnes, eight pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to be payed yerely, duryng the ſaid .iij. yeres, by euery other perſone not borne vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinges obeiſaunce, being deniſen, or no deniſen, other then women couert, ſouldiers, &amp; ſuch perſones as be vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> age of .xii. yeres, dwelli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g or reſyau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in this realme or any other y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd reliefes, ſhalbe by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aucthoritie afore ſayd: taxed aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed &amp; rated, during y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid .iii. yeres, in euery ſhere: riding, lathe, wape<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, rape, citie, Borough, toune, &amp; euery other place, within this realme of Englande, &amp; wales, &amp; other y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinges dominions, in fourme followi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g that is to ſay: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt yere before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xx. daye of Marche, &amp; the other two yeres, before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xx. daye of Ianuarie. The fyrſt paiment of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſaid relief, to be had, made &amp; paide, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> receipt of the kinges exchequer before the vi. day of May next comming. And the ſecond to be made &amp; paied, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid receipt, before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xx. day of Aprill, which ſhalbe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yere of our lord God after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> computacion of the churche of England .M.cccccl. And the third payment to be had &amp; made at the ſayd receipt, before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xx. day of Apryll which ſhalbe in the yere of our lorde .M.ccccc.li. And the ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes aboue ſayd: of and for the ſayd relief, ſhalbe taxed, ſet, aſked, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, taken, gathered, leuied, &amp; payed, vnto the vſe of our ſayd ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eraigne lord, his heyres &amp; ſucceſſours, in fourme aboue ſayd, aſwell
<pb facs="tcp:189036:3"/> within liberties, fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cheſyes, ſanctuaries, auncient demeaſne, and other whatſoeuer place exempte, or not exempt, as without. Except ſuche ſhy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, places, and perſones, as ſhalbe forpriſed, in &amp; by this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t acte: any graunt, charter, preſcription, vſe or lybertie, by reaſon of any letters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes, or other priuilege, preſcription, alowaunce of the ſame or what ſoeuer other matter of diſcharge here tofore to the contrary made grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, vſed, or obteigned notwithſtanding. And it is further enacted by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aucthorytie of this preſent parliament, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery ſuch perſon, aſwell ſuch as be borne vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinges obeiſaunce, as euery other perſon ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger borne, deniſen or not denyſen, inhabiting within this realme, or within wales, or other y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, whiche at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd aſſeſſing or taxacion yerely to be had or made, ſhalbe out of this realme, &amp; out of wales, &amp; hauè goodes or cattals, within this realme, or in wales, ſhalbe charged &amp; chargeable for the ſame, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> certificat of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inhabytauntes of the partyes, wher ſuch goodes, cattals, landes, tenementes, or other the premiſſes tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalbe, or in ſuch other place, wher ſuch perſon or his fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, deputie or attorney, ſhal haue his moſt reſorte vnto withi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, or in wales, in lyke maner as if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame perſone were or had ben at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame aſſeſſyng within this realme. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery perſon, abidi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g or dwelling within this realme, or without this realme, ſhalbe charged, and chargeable to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame relief, grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by this acte, according and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rate, of the value of his ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, goodes &amp; cattals, and other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſes, as ſuch parſon ſo to be charged, ſhalbe ſet at in the time of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid aſſeſſyng, or taxacion vpon him to be made, and in none otherwyſe.</p>
            <p>And further we the kinges ſubicctes, do geue and graunt frelye to his highnes, one other relief to be paid, yerely duryng .iij. yeres, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rcceipt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinges exchequer, after the rate &amp; in maner, &amp; fourme folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye, of euery Ewe, kept for the moſt parte of the yere, in ſeuerall ſalt, or freſhe marſhes, or in leuerall paſture, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay: groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des not commen, nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menly vſed to be tylled. .iii. pence. Of euery we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and other ſhere ſhepe kept in paſture or marſhes, as is afore ſayd, two pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. And of euery ſhere ſhepe kept, on co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons or on ſeueral grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, commenly vſed to be tylled thre half pence. To be paied yerely, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſayd .iii. yeres, by the owner, or owners of the ſame ſhepe, &amp; not by any perſon that hath the ſame ſhepe in farme, or by leaſſe, paiyng a rent ar any other profyt for the ſame, or whiche is or ſhalbe bound by any maner of couenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or ſuretie to reſtore the ſame, or as many ſhepe or the value therof at any tyme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">PROVIDED</hi> alwaies and be it enacted by the auctoritie afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd, that euery perſon not hauing aboue the nomber of ten ſhere ſhepe, ſhal paye yerely durig the ſaid .iii. yere, one halfpeny, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> polle of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuche ſhere ſhepe, and that euery perſon hauing aboue ten ſhere ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe, and not aboue .xx. ſhall paye for euery of them but one peny, duryng euery of the ſayd .iii. yeres, any thyng before in this graunt of the relief of ſhepe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined to the contrarye in any wyſe notwythſtandyng. The
<pb n="iij" facs="tcp:189036:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> fyrſt paiment of the ſaid relief of ſhepe, to be made before the fyrſt daye of Nouember, next comming: the ſeconde before the fyrſt daie of Noue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber whiche ſhalbe in the yere of our lord God .M.ccccc.l. And the third before the fyrſt daye of Nouember, which ſhalbe in the yere of our lord God M.ccccc.li.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">PROVIDED</hi> alwayes and be it ordeined and enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayd, that if the value of the ſhepe, cattall, and other moueable goodes, of him or her, that hath ſhepe chargeable to the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſaid relief, being raſed and gathered into one hole and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire ſome and value, ſhalbe found greater, and more for the aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this relief, than the payme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that ought to be made by the polle of the ſaid ſhepe, as is before declared, that then the owner of the ſayd ſhepe, ſhall not be chargeable with the payment, after the rate of the polle. And if it ſhall appere that the paiment after the rate of the polle ſhall excede in value, and be more beneficial to the king, then the money rated of the hole ſubſtaunce of any perſone: That then ſuch perſon ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſhepe ſhalbe charged to paie after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rate of the polle, and not after the value of his entier ſubſtaunce: The relief payed the yere before of his entier ſubſtaunce to be taken, and accompted as percell of the ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me that ſhalbe due and payable in the hole at the yeres ende vpon the accompt made for the polle of his ſhepe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">¶ ALSO</hi> we the kinges ſayd ſubiectes by the aucthorytie afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd, do geue and graunt vnto the kinges maieſtie, one other relief, that is to ſaye. viii. pens of the pounde, of the pryce and value of al and ſynguler wollen clothes, carſeyes, fryſes, cottons, kendales, &amp; all other kinde of wollen clothes, of what ſorte or making ſoeuer they be, that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the feaſt of the Natiuitie of ſaint Iohn Baptiſt next co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, during thre yeres then next folowing ſhalbe made by any perſone to be put to ſale, the ſame relief to be leuied and gathered yerely during the ſaid thre yeres, of the maker of the ſayd clothe, in ſuch maner and fourme as he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reafter in this acte ſhalbe declared.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">PROVIDED</hi> alwaies, and be it ordeined &amp; enacted, by the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie aforeſaid, that if it ſhall appere that the rate of. viii. pens of the pounde, of the price and value of the clothe, by ſuche clothier made as is aforeſaid, ſhall excede the rate of .xii. pence of the pounde, of his goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and cattals, that then euerye ſuche clothier, ſhall paye onely after the rate of. viii. pence of the pounde, of the clothes, &amp; not after the value of his goodes and cattals, the relief payed the fyrſt yere of his entier ſubſtaunce to be taken<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and accompted as percell of the ſomme that ſhalbe due and payable in the hole at the firſt yeres ende vpon acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pte for the clothes by hym made as is afore ſaid. The ſecond relief, paied of his entier ſubſtaunce, to be taken and accompted as percell, of the ſome that ſhalbe due and payable, in the hole at the ſecond yeres ende vpon accompt for the clothes by him made, as is afore ſaid. And the third re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief,
<pb facs="tcp:189036:4"/> payed of his entier ſubſtaunce to be taken and accompted as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of the ſomme that ſhalbe due and payable in the hole at the third yeres ende vpon accompt for the clothes by him made, as is aforeſayd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">PROVIDED</hi> alſo, and be it ordeyned and enacted by the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorytie aforeſayd, that if any perſone to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntent to defraude the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges maieſtie of the reliefs graunted by this acte, or any parte therof do coloure and take vpon him, by the aſſent or conſent, of the true owner therof, to be owner, or proprietary of any goodes, ſhepe, clothes, or other thinges chargeable to the payment of the ſayd relief, and in dede ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be founde, tryed or proued, not to be iuſt and ryght owner therof, vpon any informacion therof to be made in the kinges courte of exchequer wythin two yeres next after ſuche offence, that not onlye ſuche goodes, ſhepe, clothes, and other thinges, or the value therof ſhalbe forfayted to the kyng, but alſo the partie ſo falſelye colouring the ſame, or preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to be owner, or proprietarye of the ſame, ſhall forfeyte and loſe to the kyng, the treble value therof, to be leuied of his goodes and cattals, landes, and tenementes to the kinges vſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">AND</hi> to the entent that the kinges maieſtie may be iuſtly and truly ſatyſfied of the ſayd relief, of the value and ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of euery mannes goodes, and other ſommes, to be payed by ſiraungers, denyſens or not denyſens, by vs to his highnes geuen in maner and fourme afore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and in no part therof be defrauded, as our entent and hope is his grace ſhall not be: Be it ordeyned and enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayd, that the lord Chauncellour of Englande, the lord Threſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of England, the lord Preſydent of the kinges moſt honorable counſayll, the lord Priuie ſeale, and the lord great Chamberlayne of England, for the tyme beyng, or two of them at the leaſt, wherof the lord Chauncellour or the lord Threaſourer, to be one of them, ſhal and may name and appointe of and for euerye ſhyer, rydyng, and other places, aſwell within this realme, as in wales, and other the kinges dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as alſo for euerie citie and toune, beyng a countie of it ſelfe, and of and for the Iſle of wyght, ſuch certayne nomber of perſones of euerye of the ſame ſhyres, rydynges, lathes, wapentakes, rapes, cities, tounes, and Iſle of wight, and euerye other place, and other the inhabitauntes of the ſame, to be commiſſioners within the ſame, wherof they be inhaby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauntes, and alſo of and for the honorable houſholdes of the king our ſoueraigne lorde, the ladie Marie, and the ladye Elyzabeth graces, the kynges maieſties liſters, certayne hed officers of the ſame, to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of the ſame houſholdes, in what ſhyres or other places, the ſayd houſholdes ſhal happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then to be: &amp; the lord Chauncellour, or lord Threſaurour, and other with him before named, in like maner may na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me and appoincte of euerye other ſuche borough and toune corporat, aſwell in England, as in wales, and other the kinges dominions, as they ſhall thinke requiſyte, ſyx, fyue, foure, thre, or two, of the hed offy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers,
<pb n="iiii" facs="tcp:189036:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> and other ſad and honeſt inhabitauntes of euery of the ſayd cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, boroughes and tounes corporat, according to the nomber &amp; multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of people beyng in the ſame: the whiche perſones if any ſuche be therunto named of the ſayd inhabitauntes of the ſayd boroughes and tounes corporate, not beyng counties in them ſelfes, ſhalbe ioined and put as commiſſioners with the perſones, named for ſuch ſhyres and ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges, as the ſayd boroughes and tounes corporat not being counties in them ſelfes be ſet, &amp; haue there beyng: which perſones ſo named, for &amp; of the ſayd boroughes and tounes corporat, not beyng cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ties, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of there dwellyng in the ſame, ſhall not take vpon them, ne none of them, to put any parte of there commiſſion, in execution for the premyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, out of the ſayd borough or toune corporat, wherin they beyng ſo named onely for the ſame, be dwelling, and alſo not to execute the ſayd commiſſion, within the borough or toune coporat, wher they be ſo dwellyng, but ioyntly wyth thre at the leaſt of the other commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners wythin the ſhyre or rydyng, and in that commiſſion wherin they be ſo dwellyng, at ſuche dayes and tymes, as the ſayd other commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for the ſame ſhere and ryding, ſhal therunto lymyte and appoinct within the ſame borough or toune corporat, not beyng countie corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, wherof they ſo be, and not out of ſuch borough or toune, and in that maner to be aiding and aſſyſting, with the ſaid other commiſſioners, in and for the good executing of the effect of the ſayd commiſſion, vpon peyne of euery of the ſayd commiſſioners, ſo named for euery ſuch citie, borough, and toune corporat, not beyng a countie, to make ſuche fyne as the ſayd other commiſſioners in the commiſſion, of and for the ſayd ſhyre or riding ſo named, or thre of them at the leaſt, ſhall by there dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecions ſet and certefye into the kinges exchequer, ther to be leuyed to the vſe of our ſouereygne lord the king, in lyke maner as ſuch or lyke ſommes had ben ſet and rated vpon euery ſuch perſone for the ſayd re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief: The whiche commiſſioners ſo named, of and for the ſaid cities, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughes and tounes, not beyng counties, and only put in the ſaid com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion by reaſon of there dwellyng in the ſame, ſhall not haue any part of the porcion of the fees and rewardes for the commiſſioners, and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> clerkes in this acte, afterward ſpecifyed. And the Chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cellour of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, or keper of the kynges great Scale for the tyme beyng, ſhall make and direct out of the courte of chauncery, vnder the kinges great ſeale, ſeuerall commiſſions, that is to ſaye, to euerye ſhyre, rydyng, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, wapentake, rape, citie, toune, borough, Iſle, and houſholde, vnto ſuche perſone and perſones, as by his diſcrecion and other with hym before appoincted and named, in lyke maner and fourme as is afore reherſed, ſhalbe thought ſuffycient for the ſeſſyng and leuyeng of the ſayde relief in all ſhyres and places, accordyng vnto the true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of this acte: whiche commiſſyon ſhalbe directed and deliuered to the ſayd commiſſioners, or to one of them yerely, duryng the ſaye thre
<pb facs="tcp:189036:5"/> yeres, in maner and fourme folowyng, that is to ſaye: the fyrſt yere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the tenth daye of Marche next commyng, and the other two yeres, yerely before the fyrſt daye of Ianuary: and to euery of the ſayd com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, ten cedules, conteynyng in them the tenour of this acte, ſhalbe affyled, by the whyche commiſſion the commiſſyoners in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuche commiſſion named, according vnto this acte, or as many of them as ſhalbe appoincted by the kinges co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion, ſhall haue full po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer &amp; aucthoritie to put the effect of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame commiſſion in execucion. And that by aucthoritie of this acte, after ſuch commiſſion to them dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected yerely during the ſaid thre yeres, they may by their aſſentes and agrementes, ſeuer them ſelfes for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> execucion of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſyon, in hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dredes, lathes, wardes, rapes, wapentakes, tounes, paryſſhes, &amp; other places, within the lymytes of their ſayd commiſſyon, in ſuch fourme as to them ſhall ſeme expedient to be ordred, and betwene them to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned &amp; agreed, according to the tenour and effect of the commiſſion to them therin directed, vpon whiche ſeueraunce, euery perſon of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent parliament that ſhalbe commiſſioner, ſhalbe aſſygned in the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth where he dwelleth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">PROVIDED</hi> alwaies, that no perſone be or ſhalbe compelled to be any commiſſioner, to and for the execution of this preſent acte, but only in the ſhire where he dwelleth and inhabiteth: and that any perſon being aſſygned to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrarye therof, in any wiſe ſhal not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to put in execucion the effect of this act, or any parte therof. And it is alſo enacted by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aucthorytie of this preſent parliament, that the commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and euery of them whiche ſhalbe named, lymyted, and appoincted accordyng vnto this acte to be commiſſioners, in euerye ſuche ſhire, ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng, lathe, wapentake, rape, cytie, toune, borough, Iſle, and the ſayd houſholdes or any other place, and none other, ſhall truly, effectually &amp; dylygently for ther parte, execute the effect of this preſent acte, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to the tenour therof in euery behalfe, and none otherwyſe by any other meanes, wythout omiſſion, fauour, dread, malice, or any other thyng to be attempted and done by them, or any of them, to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hereof: and the ſaid commiſſioners, or as many of them as ſhalbe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poincted by the ſayd commiſſion, and none other, for the execution of the ſayd commiſſion, and acte, ſhall the fyrſt yere of the paiment of this relief of goodes, before the .xx. daye of Marche, and the other two ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, yerely before the .xvi. daye of Ianuary, by vertue of the commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyons, delyuered vnto them, in fourme aboueſayd, dyrect their ſeuerall or Ioynte precept vnto. viii. vii. vi. v .iiii. or thre, or moo, as for the nomber of the inhabitauntes ſhalbe requyſyte, of the moſt ſubſtanciall diſcrete, and honeſt perſones inhabytauntes, to be named by the ſaid co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners, or by as many of them as ſhalbe appoincted by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, of &amp; in hundredes, lathes, rapes, wape<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>takes, wardes, pariſhes, tounes, &amp; other places, aſwel w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in liberties, frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>chiſes au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t demeanes
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:189036:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> places exempted, and ſanctuaryes, as without, within the lymytes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhires, ridinges, lathes, wapentakes, rapes, cities, tounes, boroghes, or Iſle, aforeſaid, &amp; other places within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> limites of there commiſſion, and to the conſtables, ſubconſtables, batlliffes, &amp; other like officers or myni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, of euery of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid hundredes, tounes, wardes, lathes, wape<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>takes, pariſhes, &amp; other places before ſaid: as to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd commiſſioners, &amp; euery nomber of them vnto thre or two of them, by there diſcrecion in diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhal ſeme expedient, as by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner and vſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parties ſhalbe requiſite, ſtraitly by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame precept charging &amp; commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame inhabitau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes conſtables, &amp; other officers aforſaid to whom ſuch precept ſhalbe ſo directed to appere in their proper perſones before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners, or ſuch nomber of them as they ſhall deuide them ſelfes, according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tenour of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd commiſſion, at certain dayes &amp; places by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyoners, or any nomber of them as is aboueſayd, within cities, borou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghes, or tounes corporat, or without in any other place as is aforeſaid, by ther diſcretions ſhalbe limited therunto, to do &amp; accompliſhe all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to them on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> part of our ſoueraigne lord y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king ſhalbe enioyned touching this acte: co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunding further by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame precept, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he to whoſe handes ſuch precept ſhall come, ſhall ſhewe or delyuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame to the other inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes or officers, named in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame precept, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> none of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faile to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paine of fortie ſhillinges, to be forfaited to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">AND</hi> it is further ordeined by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid aucthoritie of this parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid daye &amp; place prefyxed, &amp; limited in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid preceptes, euery of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners, then beyng in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhyre, &amp; hauing no ſufficient excuſe for his abſence, ſhall at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd day, &amp; place prefixed for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> parte wherunto he was limited, appere in his proper perſon, &amp; there y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame commiſſioners being preſent, or as many as ſhalbe appoincted by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinges commiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhal cal or cauſe to be called before them, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd inhabitau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes &amp; officers, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei haue directed ther ſaid preceptes, &amp; which had in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ther to apere by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid precept of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners. And if any per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon ſo warned, make default onleſſe he the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be letted by ſyckneſſe or law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful excuſes, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> let then to be witneſſed by the othes of two credyble per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones: Or if any ſo appering refuſe to be ſworne in fourme folowing, to forfayte to the kyng fortie ſhyllinges: &amp; ſo at euery tyme during y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd thre yeres prefixed for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame cauſe, vnto ſuch time, the nomber of euery ſuch perſons, haue appered &amp; certefied in fourme vnder written: &amp; euery of them ſo making default, or refuſing to be ſworne, to forfaite to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king fortie ſhillinges: &amp; vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame apparaunce had, one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall inhabitauntes or officer, ſo ther being warned, &amp; appering before the ſayd commiſſyoners, ſhalbe ſworne yerely during y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid thre yeres, vpon a boke openly before the commiſſioners in fourme folowing.</p>
            <p>I ſhal truly enquire w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my fellowes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhallbe charged w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, wapentake, warde, toune, or other place, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt &amp; moſt value of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubſtaunce of euery parſon, dwellyng &amp; abiding within the limites of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> places that I and my fellowes ſhalbe charged with, &amp; of other whiche
<pb facs="tcp:189036:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſhal haue his or their moſt reſort vnto any of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid places, &amp; chargea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any ſome of money, by this acte of this ſaid relief, &amp; of al other ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſhalbe charged with, touching the ſayd acte, and accordig to the entent of the ſame, and there vpon, as nere as it may or ſhal come to my knowlege, not only truly to preſent and certefye before you, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, ſurnames, additions, and the beſt and vttermoſt ſubſtaunce and values of euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of there goodes, cattalles, dettes, &amp; other things, chargeable by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd acte, and how many ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, deniſens or not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riyſens, beyng aboue the age of .xii. yeres, be reſiau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and dwellyng w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in the lymytes of my charge, of what value in goodes and other thinges, chargeable to the payment of this relief they be, &amp; whether they be houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders or ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, or otherwiſe vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rule &amp; gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ther pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes without any conceilement, fauour, loue, affeccion, dread, feare, or malyce, ſo helpe me God, and the holy contentes of this boke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">AND</hi> euery other perſone y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhall appere there yerely by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes, ſhall make like othe, and vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> othe ſo taken as is before ſayd: by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inhabitau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes &amp; officers of euery hundred, ward, wapentake, toune, or other place, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners ſhal yerely openly there read or cauſe to be read vnto them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd rates, &amp; ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly declare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> effect of their char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge vnto them, in what maner &amp; fourme they ought &amp; ſhould make there certifycates, according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rates &amp; ſommes therof aboueſaid, and of al maner of perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, aſwel of Aliens &amp; ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, deniſens, or not denyſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, inhabyted within this realme, as of ſuch perſones as be borne within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges obeyſaunce, chargeable to this acte, &amp; of the goodes &amp; cattalles of fraternities, guildes, corporacions, brotherhedes, miſteriers, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and cominalties &amp; other, as is aboue ſaid: and of perſons being in the parties of beyond y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea, hauing goodes or catals within this realme as is before ſayd: &amp; of all goodes being in cuſtody to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of any other, as is aboue ſaid: by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which informacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſhewing, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd perſons ſhal haue ſuch playn knowlege of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true entent of this preſent acte, &amp; of the manour of ther certificat, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame perſons ſhall haue no reaſonable cauſe to excuſe them by ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. And after ſuch othes, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtatute of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid relief, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner of the ſaid certificat, to be made in writting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teining y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> names, ſurnames, and additions of euery perſone, &amp; whether he be borne without y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinges obeiſaunce or within, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt value of euery perſone in euery degre, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> value of goodes, and cattals, dettes, and euery thing to their ſayd certificat, requiſite and neceſſarye to them declared: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd commiſſioners ther beyng, ſhall by ther diſcretions ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poinct &amp; limite vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid perſones, an other daye &amp; place to apere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſayd commiſſioners, &amp; charging y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd perſones, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they in the meane tyme ſhal make diligent enquiry by al waies &amp; meanes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes, &amp; then &amp; ther euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paine of forfaiture of .xx. ſheli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king, to appere at the ſaid new prefixed daie &amp; place, ther to certifye vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners in writing, according to there ſaid charge, &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of relief, &amp; as to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in maner afor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:189036:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> hath ben declared &amp; ſhewed by the commiſſyoners, at which daye &amp; place ſo to them prefixed, if any of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd perſones make default, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere &amp; refuſe to make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd certificat: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> then euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, to forfayte to the king fortye ſhyllynges: Except only a reaſonable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe for his default by reaſon or ſycknes or otherwiſe by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> othes of two credyble perſones there witneſſed be had: &amp; of ſuche as appere redy to make certificat, as is afore ſaid y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners ther being ſhal ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke and receiue the ſame certifycat &amp; euery parte therof, and the names values and ſubſtaunce of euery perſone ſo certifyed: And if the ſame co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners ſe cauſe reaſonable, they ſhal examine y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid preſentoures therof, &amp; there vpon the ſayd commiſſioners at the ſayd dayes &amp; place by there agrement among them ſelfes ſhall yerely during the ſayd thre yeres, openly ther prefyx a daye at a certain place or places with in the lymites of there commiſſion by their diſcrecion, for their further proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſayd aſſcſſyng of the ſame relief, and there vpon at the ſayd daye of the ſaid cettifycat (as is before ſayd) taken, the ſame commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſhal make their precept or preceptes to the conſtables, ſubconſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, bailiffes or other officers of ſuch hundredes, wapentakes, tounes or other places afore ſayd, as the ſame commiſſioners ſhalbe of, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng &amp; conteyning in the ſame precept the names, ſurnames &amp; additio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of all perſones preſented before them in the ſayd certificates: of whome if the ſayd commiſſioners or as many of them as ſhalbe therunto ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poincted by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinges commiſſion ſhal then haue veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſuſpect to be of more greater value or ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in goodes, cattals or ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney owing to them, or other ſubſtaunce before ſaid, then vpon ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſones ſhalbe certefyed, the ſame co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners ſhal make there precept or preceptes directed to the conſtable, bailyffes, and other offy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, commaunding y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame conſtables bailiffes &amp; other officers, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch precept ſhalbe directed to warne ſuch perſones whoſe names ſhall be compriſed in the ſaid precept, at there mancions or to their perſones, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame perſones named in ſuch preceptes &amp; euery of them, ſhal per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally appere before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid commiſſioners at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame new prefyxed day and place, ther to be ſworne &amp; examined by al wayes and meanes by the ſaid commiſſioners of ther greateſt ſubſtaunce and beſt value, and of al and euery ſommes of money owing to them, and other whatſoeuer mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> premiſſes or any of them, accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to this acte. At which daye and place ſo prefyxed, the ſayd commiſſioners than there beyng, or as many of them as ſhalbe theru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to appoincted by the kynges co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhall cauſe to be called the ſayd perſones, whoſe names ſhalbe compry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid precept, as it is before ſaid for their examinacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And if any of the perſones whiche ſhould be warned, as is before ſayd, to be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whiche at any tyme after the warning, and before the prefyxed day ſhalbe within ſuch place, wher he may haue knowlege of the ſayd appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to be made, make default &amp; appere not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> onleſſe a reſonable cauſe, or els a reaſonable excuſe by the othes of two credyble perſones before the
<pb facs="tcp:189036:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſayd commiſſyoners be truely alleged for his diſcharge, that then euery of them ſo makinge default, to be taxed and charged to the king with &amp; at the double ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes of the rate that he ſhould or ought to haue ben ſet at, for and after the beſt value of his goodes &amp; ſubſtaunce vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefied, if he had appered, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſcrecion of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners there being. And in like maner if any of them ſuſpected, as is before ſayd, appere &amp; refuſe to be ſworne in fourme folowing: then euery ſuche offender to be taxed and charged to the king with and at the double ſomme of the rate that he ſhould or ought to haue ben ſet at, for &amp; after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt value of his ſubſtaunce vpon him certefied by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid perſones y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> made the certificat, as is before ſaid, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſcrecions of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners ther than beyng &amp; euery of the perſones ſo ther &amp; then apperyng: Whoſe names ſhalbe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the ſaid precept or preceptes, &amp; in whom any vehement ſuſpect was or ſhalbe had in fourme aboue ſayd, ſhall trauell with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone ſo ſuſpecte, by all ſuche waies &amp; meanes they can: And further the ſayd Commiſſioners, or as many of them as ſhalbe hereunto appoinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the ſaid Commiſſion, by ther diſcrecion ſhall openly ſwere y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame perſon in this maner and fourme folowing.</p>
            <p>¶ I ſhall faythfully, truly, and plainly according to my knowlege, ſhew vnto you the kinges Commiſſioners, and to other by you aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the beſt and greateſt value or aboue of all my goodes &amp; Cattals, &amp; ſomes of money to me owing, accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of this acte of relief, &amp; truly aunſwer to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſhalbe examined of, touchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the premiſſes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out couyn or deceipt, ſo helpe me God, &amp; the holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentes of this boke.</p>
            <p>And if any perſone that ſhoulde appere be excuſed in fourme afore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaid by witnes of credyble perſones, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame perſones ſhalbe examyned by their othes of his or their greateſt and beſt value and ſubſtaunce ſo lacking and excuſed, and by the beſt of ther certifycat or knowlege, or of the other firſt certifycat vpon him or the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made, the ſame perſone ſo lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and excuſed of his apparaunce to be ſet and rated by the ſaid Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, or otherwiſe to be ſet and rated in this caſe as ſhall ſeme beſt by the diſcretions of the ſaid Commiſſioners. And if it happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by witnes, his owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or other lawful waies or meanes, withe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one yere after any ſuch othe made, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame perſon ſo taxed and ſwore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, was of any greater or better value in goodes or other thinges aboue ſpecifyed at the tyme of his ſaid othe, then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame perſone ſo ſworne did declare vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his othe: That the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch perſone ſo offending ſhal loſe &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayte to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king foure tymes ſo much in lawful money or England as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame perſone ſo ſworne was ſet &amp; taxed at, to paie for the ſayd Relief.</p>
            <p>And if any perſon certefied or rated by vertue of this acte, be he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner or other, to any maner of value, do fynd him ſelfe greued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame preſentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſeſſyng or taxing, &amp; ther vpon complain to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſyoners, before who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhalbe rated, ſeſſed or taxed, or before two of them, that then the ſaid Commiſſioners, ſhall by all wayes and meanes examine particularlye &amp; diſtynctlye the perſone ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plainaunt &amp; other
<pb n="vij" facs="tcp:189036:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> his neighbours, by their diſcrecion, of euery his goodes, cattalles &amp; deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes aboue mencioned, and after due examinacion, and perfect knowlege therof had and perceiued by theſaied Commiſſioners<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whiche ſhall haue power, by aucthoritie aforeſaid: theſaid Commiſſioners, or two of theim to whom any ſuche complaint ſhalbee made by their diſcrecions, vpon the othe of theſaid perſon ſo complainyng, maie abate, defalke, encreaſe, or enlarge theſame aſſeſſement, accordyng as it ſhall appere to theim iuſt vpon theſaid examinacion, and theſame ſomme ſo abated, defalked, encreaſed, or enlarged by theim, to bee ſtreated in forme as hereafter en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſueth, ſo that he come before the extreates of theſaid aſſeſſyng be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by theſaied Commiſſioners into the kynges Exchequer. And if it be proued by witnes, his awne confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or other lawfull waies or meanes within a yere after any ſuche othe made, that theſame perſone ſo taxed &amp; ſworne, was of any greater or better value in goodes, or other thynges aboue ſpecified, at the tyme of his ſaied othe then theſame perſone ſo ſworne, did declare vpon his ſaied othe: that then euery ſuche perſone ſo offendyng, ſhal loſe &amp; forfaite to the kyng .iiii. tymes ſo muche in lawful money of Englande, as theſame perſone ſo ſworne, was ſet at or taxed to paie. And all perſones, ſette, rated and taxed as is aforeſaied, ſhalbee bounde and charged by theſame: and the ſomme or ſommes vpon hym ſet, to bee due towardes the paiment of this relief, and to bee leuied as hereafter ſhalbe ſpecified.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">AND</hi> it is alſo enacted by theſaid aucthoritie, that euery perſon ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely duryng theſaid .iii. yeres, as is aforeſaid, ſhalbe rated, taxed and ſet and the ſome on hym ſet to be leuied at ſuche place, wher he &amp; his family at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of theſame preſentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be made, ſhal kepe his houſe or dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng, or where he then ſhalbe moſte conuerſaunt abidyng or reſiaunt, or ſhall haue his moſte reſort, and ſhalbee beſt knowen at the tyme of the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaied certificat to bee made, and no where els. And that no Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner for this Relief of goodes, ſhalbe rated or taxed for his goodes, but in the ſhire, citie, or other place, where he dwelleth and is Commiſſioner. And if any perſone chargeable to this Acte, at the tyme of theſaid aſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng, happen to be out of this realme, and out of Wales, or farre from the place where he ſhalbe knowen, then he to bee ſet where he was laſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidyng, in this realme or within Wales, and beſt knowen. And after the ſubſtaunce and value of euery perſone, knowen by the examinacion, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificat, and other maner of wiſe, as is aforſaid, theſaied Commiſſioners or as many of theim as ſhalbe appoyncted by the kynges Commiſſion, ſhall after the rate aforeſaid, ſet and taxe euery perſon, accordyng to the rate of ſubſtaunce, and value of his goodes and cattalles: whereby the greateſt and moſte beſt ſomme, accordyng to his moſte ſubſtaunce, by reaſon of this act, ought or maie be ſet or taxed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">BE</hi> it alſo ordeigned by theſaid aucthoritie, that no perſone hauyng twoo mancions, or twoo places to reſort vnto, or callyng hymſelf houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde
<pb facs="tcp:189036:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſeruaunt or waityng ſeruaunt, to the kynges highnes, his graces ſiſters, or to any noble man or woman, ſhalbe excuſed vpon his ſaiyng, from the taxe of theſaied relief in neither of the places where he maie bee ſette, onleſſe he bryng a certificat in writyng from the Commiſſioners, where that he is ſo ſet in deede at one place. And if any happen to bee ſet in twoo places, vpon certificat thereof made, the beſt and moſte ſomme vpon hym ſo taxed, to bee taken and abyde, and the other to bee diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, ſo that theſame certificat of his aſſeſſyng and paiment, bee made thereof in writyng, vnder the ſeales of the Commiſſioners, or of as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theim as ſhalbee appoyncted by the kynges Commiſſion: whiche certificat ſo made, ſhalbe at all tymes a ſufficient diſcharge for hym, and the Collectour of theſame, aſwell againſt any Collectour, that ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde theſame vpon hym rated or taxed, as againſt the kyng and all other perſones.</p>
            <p>And if any perſone that ought to bee ſet, by reaſon of his remouyng or reſortyng to two places, or by reaſon of his ſaiyng, that he els where was taxed, or by reaſon of any priuilege, by his dwellyng or abidyng in any place, not beyng forepriſed in this Acte, or any otherwiſe by his couyn or crafte, happen to eſcape from the yerely aſſeſſyng, and bee not ſette, and that proued by preſentment, examinacion or informacion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſaied Commiſſioners, or as many of theim as ſhalbe by theſame Commiſſion appoyncted, or by the Barones of the kynges Exchequer, or twoo Iuſtices of the Peace of that countrey, where ſuche perſone dwelleth: then euery ſuche perſone, that by ſuche meanes or other wyſe, wilfully by couyn, ſhall happen to eſcape from the aſſeſſyng of the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaied reliefes, or of any of theim, and not bee rated, taxed, and ſet, ſhalbe charged vpon the knowlege and proffe thereof, with, and at the double value that he ſhould, or ought to haue been ſette at afore, accordyng to his behauoure: theſame double value to bee leuied, gathered and paied of his goodes, and cattalles, landes and tenementes, towardes theſaid relief, and further to bee puniſhed, accordyng to the diſcrecions of the Barones, Iuſtices, or Commiſſioners, before whom he ſhalbe conuicted for his offence and deceipt in that behalfe.</p>
            <p>And it is further ordeigned and enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſaid, that not onely euery aſſeſſour ſhalbe rated, taxed and aſſeſſed yerely, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng theſaied three yeres, for the value of his goodes and cattalles, by the Commiſſioners, or the moſte part of theim, by whom he is appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to bee an aſſeſſour, but alſo that euery Commiſſioner aſſigned and deputed, for the orderyng, taxyng, ratyng, and leuiyng of this relief, graunted to the kynges Maieſtie, of twelue pence of the pounde, of the value of euery mannes goodes, dwellyng within the precinct and limit of his Commiſſion, for his awne ſubſtaunce in goodes, ſhalbe ſeſſed, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed, valued and rated yerely, duryng theſaied three yeres, by the exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion and ſeſſyng of the reſt of the Commiſſioners, named in theſame
<pb n="viij" facs="tcp:189036:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> Commiſſion, or the moſte part of theim, after ſuche value of his goodes and cattalles, as is mencioned in this Acte. And that all perſones of the eſtate of a Baro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or Baroneſſe, not being maried, and euery eſtate aboue ſhalbe examined and charged, of the paiment of this relief of their goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, before the lorde Chauncellor, the Lorde Theaſaurer of Englande, and lorde priuey ſeale for the tyme beyng, or other perſones by the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges aucthoritie to be limited: and thei to bee charged yerely, duryng the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid thre yeres, for their goodes and ſubſtaunce, accordyng to their exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minacion aforeſaied. And the ſommes vpon them ſet, with the names of the Collectours appoyncted, for the gatheryng and paiyng of theſame, be extreated, deliuered, and certified at daies and places aboue ſpecified by theſaied Chauncellor, Theaſaurer, and lorde priuey Seale for the tyme beyng, or ſuche other perſones, as ſhalbe appoyncted by the Kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges highnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">AND</hi> it is further ordeined and enacted, by thaucthoritie aforeſaid, that after the Taxes and Aſſeſſementes, of theſaied ſommes, vpon and and by theſaied examinacion and certificat, as is aforeſaied made, the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaied Commiſſioners ſhall yerely duryng theſaied three yeres, within .x. daies nexte after the Taxacion and Aſſeſſement, of paiment of theſaied Relief, by writyng Indented to bee made of theſaied Taxacion and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſement, vnder the ſeales and ſignes manuelles of theſaied Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners, deliuer vnto ſufficient and ſubſtanciall inhabitauntes, Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, Subconſtables, Bayliffes, or other officers ioyntly of Hundredes. Tounes, Pariſhes, and other places aforeſaied within their limites, or to other ſufficient perſones, inhabitauntes of theſame, onely by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theſame Commiſſioners, and as the place and parties ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, aſwell the particular names and ſurnames, as the remembraunce of all ſommes of money, Taxed and ſett of and vpon euery perſone, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well manne as woman chargeable to this Act, houſholder, and al other inhabitauntes and dwellers, and all Fraternities, Guyldes, Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, Miſteries, Brotherhoddes, Compaignies and Cominalties, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porat or not corporat, within theſaied Pariſhes, tounes &amp; places, contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butory to this Act of relief. By aucthoritie of whiche writyng, or eſtreat ſo deliuered, theſaid officers or other perſones ſo named and deputed ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerally, ſhall haue full power and aucthoritie by vertue of this act, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly after the deliuery of theſaid writyng or eſtreate, to demaunde, leuie, and gather of euery perſone and Fraternitie, Guyld, Corporacion Miſtery, Brotherhod, Compaignie, and Comminaltie, corporate or not corporate therin ſpecified, the ſomme or ſommes in theſame writyng or eſtreat co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>priſed. And for non paiment therof to diſtrain the goodes and cattalles, of ſuche perſone, Fraternitie, Guylde, Corporacion, Miſtery, Brotherhod, Compaignie and Comminaltie, corporat or not corporat, and the diſtreſſe ſo taken, to kepe by the ſpace of eight daies, at the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes and charges of the owners thereof: And if theſaied owner doo not
<pb facs="tcp:189036:9"/> paie ſuche ſomme of money, as ſhalbe taxed by this acte, within the ſame viii. daies, then theſaid diſtreſſe to be appriſed, by .iiii .iii. or two of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitantes, where ſuche diſtreſſe is taken, and alſo to be ſolde by theſaid Conſtable and other collector for the paiment of theſaid money: and the ouerplus commyng of the ſale and kepyng thereof (if any be) to bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly reſtored to the owner of the ſame diſtreſſe, whiche ſaied officers and other perſones ſo deputied to aſke, take, gather, and leuie the ſaied ſommes, ſhall anſwere and bee charged for their porcion, onely to theim aſſigned or limited, to be gathered, leuied, and compriſed in the ſaied wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng or eſtreate, to theim as is aforeſaied deliuered, vnto the vſe of our ſouereigne lorde the kyng, his heires and ſucceſſors, and theſaid ſomme in that writyng or eſtreat co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>priſed, to pay vnto the high collector or col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors, of that place for the colleccion of the ſame, in maner and fourme vnder written, to be named and deputed: and the ſame inhabitau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes and officers, ſo gatheryng the ſame perticular ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes, for their colleccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſhall reteigne for euery .xx. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ſo by theim receiued and paied .ii. d. and that to be allowed at the paiment of their colleccion, by them to be made to the high collector or collectors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">PROVIDED</hi> alwaies, and be it ordeigned and enacted, by thau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cthoritie aforeſaid, that if any perſone not beyng the kynges ſubiect na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally borne, deniſen or not deniſen, beyng aboue the age of .xii. yeres, &amp; not worth .xx. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. in goodes, and be at the tyme of the paiment of the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes, of. viii. d. due by this acte of euery ſuche perſone, or at any tyme du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng theſaid thre yeres, in ſeruice with any man or woman, or vnder the gouernaunce of his or her father or mother, that euery ſuche Maſter or Maiſtres, father or mother, ſhalbe charged with the paiment therof, for ſuche perſon in like maner and fourme, as he or ſhe is or ought to be for the reliefes due by themſelfes. And that it ſhalbee lefull for euery ſuche Maſter and Maiſtres to defalke, abate, and reteigne of the wages of ſuche ſeruaunt, ſo muche as he or ſhe had before paied for ſuche ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t towardes the paiment of theſaied reliefes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">AND</hi> further bee it enacted by theſaied aucthoritie of this preſent Parliament, that theſaid commiſſioners, ſhall yerely duryng theſaid .iii. yeres, name ſuche ſufficient and able perſones, whiche then ſhall haue &amp; poſſede landes, or other hereditamentes in their awne right, of the yere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly value of .x. l. or goodes to the value of an. C. marke at the leſt, and the ſame perſones ſeuerally, by the diſcrecions of the ſame commiſſioners in ſhires, Ridynges, Lathes, Wapentakes, Rapes, cities, tounes corporat, and other whatſoeuer places, aſwel within places priuileged as without not beyng forpriſed in this act, to be high collectors<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; haue the colleccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and receipt of theſaied ſommes, ſet &amp; leuiable within the precinct, limites and bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, where thei ſhalbee ſo limited to gather &amp; receiue: to euery of the whiche collectors ſo ſeuerally named, theſaid co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners, or two of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the leſt, yerely duryng theſaid .iii. yeres, within .xii. daies next after
<pb n="ix" facs="tcp:189036:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> theſaied whole ſomme of theſaid reliefes, ſhalbe ſet and rated by all the limites of the ſame their commiſſion, or in ſuche limites as the high col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors ſhalbe ſo ſeuerally aſſigned, ſhall vnder their ſeales and ſignes manuell, deliuer one eſtreate indented in parcheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to euery of the ſame high collectors, compriſyng in it the names of all ſuche perſones, as wer aſſigned to leuie theſaied particular ſommes, and the ſommes of euery hundred, Wapentake, toune, or other place aforeſaid, with the names &amp; ſurnames of the perſones ſo chargeable, accordyng to the eſtrete ſo firſt thereof made (as is beforeſaied) and deliuered: and the collector ſo to bee aſſigned, ſhalbe charged to aunſwere the whole ſomme, compriſed in the ſaied eſtrcate limited to his colleccion, as is aforeſaied.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">PROVIDED</hi> alwaies and be it enacted by thauctoritie aforſaid, that theſaid commiſſioners hauyng aucthoritie by this act, to name the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaied high collectors of theſaied reliefes, yerely duryng theſaied thre ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, ſhall immediatly vpon their nominacion and eleccion, take by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cthoritie of this preſent Parliament, ſufficient Recogniſaunces or Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligacions, without any fee or reward to be paied therefore, of euery per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone ſo by theim to bee named to bee high Collector, to bee bound to the kyng in the double ſomme, of the ſomme of his colleccion, and to bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorced and made vpon ſuche condicion, that if theſaied Collectour, his Heires or Executors, do truly content and paie, to the vſe of the kyng, his Heires, or Executours, in his receipte of his Exchequer, before the daie appoyncted by this acte, ſo muche of theſaied ſomme of money, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted and appoyncted to his colleccion, as he ſhall Collect and gather, and content and paie the reſidue of his Colleccion and charge, within one moneth next after ſuche tyme, as he hath gathered and collected the ſame reſidue: that then theſaid recogniſaunce or obligacion to be voyd, or els to ſtand in his ful ſtrength and vertue. Whiche recogniſaunce or obligacion ſo taken theſaid co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners ſhall certifie &amp; deliuer into the Kynges Exchequer, with the certificat of theſaied taxacion and rate of theſaied relief, at and by the tyme to theim preſcribed and appoyncted by this act, vpon pein of forfeiture of .x. l. to the kyng, for euery recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunce or obligacion not certified. And that euery ſuch collector ſo elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, named and choſen, vpon requeſt to hym made, ſhall knowlege and make theſaid recogniſaunce or obligacion, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> like pein and forfeiture of .x. l. to the kyng, for the refuſal therof: and euery ſuche collector, ſo ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely deputed, hauyng theſaied eſtreate in patchement, as is aforeſaied<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhall haue aucthoritie by this act, yerely duryng theſaied three yeres, to appoynct daies and places, within the circuite of his Colleccion, for the paiment of theſaied relief to hym to bee made, and thereof to geue war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng by Proclamacion or otherwiſe, to all theſaid Conſtables, or other perſones or inhabitauntes, hauyng the charge of the particular collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, within the Hundredes, Pariſhes; Tounes, or other places by hym or them limited, to make paiment for their ſaied particuler colleccion of
<pb facs="tcp:189036:10"/> euery ſome, as to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall appertein. And if at theſaid daie &amp; place ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited and prefixed by theſaid collector, theſaied Conſtables, officers, or other perſones or inhabitauntes (as is aforeſaied) for theſaid particuler colleccion appoyncted and aſſigned within ſuche hundred, citee, toune, or other place, do not paie vnto theſaid collectors, the ſome within their ſeuerall hundredes, tounes, Pariſhes, and other places, due &amp; compriſed in theſaid eſtrcates thereof to them deliuered by theſaid commiſſioners, as is before ſaid, or ſo muche therof as thei haue by any meane receiued (ii. d. of euery pound for theſaied particuler colleccion, as is beforeſaied, alwaies to be therof allowed, excepted &amp; abated) that then it ſhalbe law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to theſaid high collectors, and euery of them, and to their aſſignes, to diſtrain euery of theſaied Conſtables, officers, and other inhabitaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes for their ſaied ſeuerall and particuler colleccion of theſaid ſommes, compriſed in theſaied eſtreate and writyng therof, to them and euery of them, as is before expreſſed deliuered: or for aſmuche of the ſame ſomme, as ſo then ſhall happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be gathered and leuied, beyng behynd and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paied, by the goodes and cattalles, of euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo beyng behind: and the diſtreſſe ſo taken, to be kept appreiſed and ſold, as is aforeſaid: and therof to take and leuy the ſome ſo then beyng behynd and vnpaied, and the ouerplus commyng of the ſale of theſaied diſtreſſe (if any bee) to bee reſtored and deliuered vnto the owner, in forme aboue remembred.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">PROVIDED</hi> alwaies, that no perſone inhabited in any citce, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough, or toune corporat, ſhalbe compelled to be an aſſeſſor or collector, of, or for any part of theſaid relief, in any place or places, out of theſaied Citee, Borough, or toune, corporate where he dwelleth. And it is alſo by theſaid aucthoritie enacted, that if any inhabitaunt or officer, or whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer perſone or perſones charged, to, and for the colleccion or receipt, of any part or porcion of theſaid relief, in any of theſaid thre yeres, by any maner of meane, accordyng to this act, or any perſon or perſones for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes, or as keper, deputie, factor or atturney, of, and for any other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons, of any goodes and cattalles, and the owner therof at the tyme of theſaid aſſeſſyng to be made, beyng out of this realme, or in any other parties not knowen, or of, and for the goodes and cattalles of any other perſon or perſones, or of any corporacion, fraternitie, guyld, miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, compainy, or other whatſoeuer comminaltie, beyng incorporat or not incorporate, and all perſones hauyng in their rule, gouernaunce, or cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody, any goodes or cattalles, at the tyme of theſaid aſſeſſyng, or any of them to be made, or whiche for any cauſe, for, &amp; by colleccion or for hym ſelf, or for any other, or by reaſon that he hath the rule, gouernaunce, or cuſtody of any goodes or cattalles, of any other perſon or perſones tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie, Guylde, Corporacion, Cominaltie, Compaignie, or Miſtery, or any ſuche other like or as factor deputie, or attorney, of or for any perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhalbee taxed, rated, valued, and ſet to any ſomme or ſommes, by reaſon of this act: and after the taxacion or aſſeſſyng, vpon any ſuche perſon or
<pb n="x" facs="tcp:189036:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> perſones, as ſhalbe charged with the receipt of the ſame, happen to die or depart from the place, where he was ſo taxed and ſet, or his goodes and cattalles to bee ſo eloyned, or in ſuche priuie and couert maner kept, as theſaid perſone or perſones charged with the ſame, by extreates or other writyng fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſaid commiſſioners, cannot ne may leuy tht ſame ſome or ſomes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>priſed within their ſaid extreates by diſtreſſe, within the limites of their colleccion, as is beforſaid, or ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſel ſuche diſtreſſe, or diſtreſſes as be taken for any of theſaid yerely paimentes, before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme limited to the high collector, for his paime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be made in the kynges receipt: then vpon relacion therof made, with due examinacion by the othe or exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion of ſuche perſone or perſones, as ſhalbe charged with, and for the receipt and colleccion of the ſame, before theſaied commiſſioners, or one of them, or before the high collector or collectors, where ſuche perſone or perſons or other, as is aforeſaid, their goodes and cattalles wer ſet and taxed: and vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> plain certificat therof, made into the kynges Exchequer, by the ſame commiſſioners, or any one of them, or vpon the othe of one of the high collectors, in theſaid court of thexchequer, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dwellyng place, names and ſommes of theſaid perſones, of whom theſaid ſommes ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be leuied &amp; had, as is beforeſaied, then aſwell the Conſtables and other inhabitauntes, appoincted for the particuler colleccion, againſt the high collectors, as the high collector, vpon his accompt and othe in theſaied Exchequer, to be diſcharged therof, and proceſſe to be made for the kyng out of theſaied Exchequer, by the diſcrecions of the Barons of theſaied Exchequer, againſt ſuche perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, his heires or executors, ſo beyng behind with his paiment. And ouer that the ſame co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any ſuch declaracion of the premiſſes, ſhalbe made in forme aforeſaid, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tyme to tyme, ſhall haue full power &amp; aucthoritie, duryng theſaid .iii. yeres, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect their precept or preceptes, vnto theſaid perſon or perſones, charged with any ſome, of, for or vpon any ſuch perſon or perſons, or other as is aboueſaid, or to any ſhirieffes, ſtewardes, bailieffes, or other whatſoeuer officer, miniſter, perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, of ſuche place or places, where any ſuche perſon or perſons, ſo owyng ſuche ſome or ſommes, ſhall haue landes &amp; teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, or other hereditamentes, or real poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, goodes or cattals, wherby any ſuche perſon or perſons ſo indebted, his heires, executors, or aſſignes, or other hauyng the cuſtody, gouernaunce, or diſpoſicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of any goodes, cattals, la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, tenementes, or other hereditame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes which ought or may by this act lawfully be diſtreined, or taken for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>ſame, hath &amp; ſhal haue goodes, cattals, la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, &amp; other poſſeſſions, wherof ſuche ſome or ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes, whiche by any ſuche perſon or perſons, maie or ought to bee leuied, be it within the limite of ſuche commiſſion, where ſuche perſon or perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, was or wer taxed, or without in any place within this realme of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, Wales, or other the kynges dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Marches or territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: by whiche precept aſwel ſuche perſon, or perſons as ſhalbe charged to lcuie ſuche money, as thofficers of the place or places, where ſuche di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe
<pb facs="tcp:189036:11"/> ſtreſſe maie bee taken, ſhall haue full power and aucthoritie, to diſtreine euery ſuche perſone indebted, charged or chargeable by this acte, or his executors or adminiſtrators of his goodes and cattals, his factors, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties, leſſees, fermours and aſſignes, and all other perſones, by whoſe handes or out of whoſe landes any ſuche perſone, ſhould haue rent, fee, annuitie, or any other proffite, or whiche at the tyme of theſaid aſſeſſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſhal haue goodes or cattalles, or any other thyng moueable, of any ſuche perſone or perſones beyng indebted, or owyng ſuche ſomme. And the diſtreſſe ſo take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to cauſe to be kept appreiſed and ſold, in like maner and forme, as is aforeſaid, for the diſtreſſe to be taken vpon perſones, to be taxed to theſaid relief, and beyng ſufficient to diſtrein, within the limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the collectors, inhabitauntes, or other officers charged with or for theſame ſommes, ſo vpon theim to be taxed. And if any ſuche diſtreſſe for none paiment, happen to be taken out of the limite of the perſones char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and aſſigned to leuie theſame, the perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſo charged for the leuiyng of euery ſuche ſomme by diſtreſſe, ſhall perceiue and take of theſame di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, for the labor of euery perſon, goyng for thexecucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof, for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mile that any ſuche perſon ſo laboreth for theſame .ii. d. And euery fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, tenaunt, factor, or other whatſoeuer perſone beeyng diſtreined, or other wiſe charged for paiment of any ſuche ſomme or ſommes, or any other ſomme, by reaſon of this act, ſhalbe of ſuche ſomme or ſommes, of hym or them ſo leuied and taken, diſcharged &amp; acquited at his nexte daie of paiment of theſame, or at the deliuery of ſuche goodes and cattalles, as he that is ſo diſtreined had in his cuſtodie or gouernaunce, againſt him or them that ſhalbe ſo taxed and ſet: any graunt or writyng obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, or other whatſoeuer matter to the contrary made heretofore not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng. And if any ſuche perſon, that ſhould be ſo diſtreined, haue no landes or tenementes ſufficient, wherby he or his tenauntes, and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors maie be diſtreined, or hath eloyned, alyened or hid his goodes and cattalles, wherby he ſhould or might be diſtreined, in ſuche maner that ſuche goodes and cattalles ſhall not bee knowen, or founde, ſo that the ſomme by hym to be paied in theſaid forme, ſhall ne can be conueniently leuied<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then vpon relacion thereof vnto the Commiſſioners, where ſuche perſone or perſones was taxed and ſet, by the othes of hym or them, that ſhalbe charged with the leuy &amp; paiment of that ſome or ſommes, theſame commiſſioners ſhal make a precept, in ſuche maner as is aforſaid, for to attache, take &amp; arreſt the body, of ſuche perſon or perſones, that ought to paie theſaid ſommes, &amp; by this act ſhalbe charged with and for theſame ſomme or ſommes, and them ſo taken ſafely to kepe in priſon, within the ſhire or other place, where any ſuche perſon or perſons ſhalbe take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and attached there to remain without baile or mainpriſe, vntil he haue paied the ſomme or ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes, that ſuche perſones for hymſelf or for any other, by this act ſhalbe chargeable, or ought to be charged withall, &amp; alſo for the fees of euery ſuche arreſt to hym or the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhal execute ſuch precept .xx. d.
<pb n="xj" facs="tcp:189036:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> And that euery officer, vnto whom ſuche precept ſhalbe directed, do his true diligence to execute theſame, vpon euery perſone ſo beyng indebted vpon pein to forfaict to our ſaied ſouereigne Lorde the Kyng, for euery default in that behalfe .xx. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And that no keper of any gaile, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his gaile ſuffre any ſuche perſon to go at large by lettyng to baile, or otherwiſe to depart out of his priſon, before he haue paied his ſaied debt, and theſaid xx. d. for theſaied arreſt, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pein to forfaite to our ſouereigne lorde .xl. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and theſame gailer to paie vnto our ſaied ſouereigne Lorde, the double value aſwell of the rate, whiche theſaid perſone ſo impriſoned was taxed at, as of theſaied .xx. d. for the fees. And like proceſſe and remedy in like fourme ſhalbe graunted by theſaied commiſſioners, at like informacion of euery perſone or perſones, beyng charged with any ſomme of money for any other perſone or perſones, by reaſon of theſaied reliefes, euery of theſaid thre yeres, and not therof paied, but wilfully withdrawen, ne the ſame leuiable within the limite where ſuche perſon was therunto taxed. And if the ſomme or ſommes, beyng behynd vnpaied, by any perſone or perſones, as is before ſaied, bee leuied and gathered by force of theſaied proceſſe, to be made by theſame comiſſioners, or if in default, or for lacke of paiment thereof, the perſone or perſones ſo owyng theſaied ſomme or ſommes of money, by proceſſe of theſame commiſſioners to be made (as is aforeſaied) be committed to priſon in forme aboue ſaied, that then the ſaied commiſſioners, whiche ſhall award ſuche proceſſe, ſhall make cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificat therof in theſaid Exchequer, of that ſhalbe doen in the premiſſes, in the Terme next folowyng, after ſuche ſomme or ſommes of money ſo beyng behynd, ſhalbe leuied, and gathered, or ſuche perſone or perſones for none paiment of theſame committed to priſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> if it happen any of theſaied collectors, to bee aſſigned, or any Maior, Sherif, Steward, Conſtables, hedboroughes, houſholder, bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, or any other officer or miniſter, or other whatſoeuer perſon or perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to diſobey theſaied co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in the reaſonable requeſt to them made, by theſaied commiſſioners, for yerely execucion of theſaid co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion, duryng theſaied .iii. yeres: or if any of thofficers or other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones, do refuſe that to theim ſhall appertein or belong to do, by reaſon of any precept to him or the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be directed, or any reaſonable commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, inſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or requeſt touchyng the premiſſes, or other default in any apparau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or colleccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do make, or if any perſon beyng ſuſpect or not to be indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly taxed, as is afore ſaid, do refuſe to be examined according to the tenor of this act, before theſaied commiſſioners, or as many of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ſhalbe therunto aſſigned, as is aforeſaid, or wil not appere before the ſame co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners, vpon warnyng to hym made, or els make reſiſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or reſkous vpon any diſtreſſe, vpon him to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for any percell of the ſaid relief, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit any miſbehauor in any maner of wiſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to this act, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit any wilfull omiſſion, or other whatſoeuer wilfull none do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng or miſdoyng, contrary to the tenor of this act or graunt: theſame co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners,
<pb facs="tcp:189036:12"/> or twoo of them at the leaſt, vpon probable knowlege of any ſuch miſdemeanours, had by informacion or examinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhall and maie ſet vpon euery ſuche offendour, for euery ſuche offence in name of a fine, by theſame offendor to be forfeited .xx. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. or vnder, by the diſcrecio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame Commiſſioners. And further, theſaid commiſſioners, &amp; euery nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to two of them at the le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, ſhal haue aucthoritie by this preſent Parliament, to poniſhe euery ſuche offendor by impriſonment, there to remaigne and to bee deliuered by their diſcrecion, as ſhall ſeme to theim conuenient. Theſaied fines (if any ſuche bee) to bee certified by theſaied commiſſioners, that ſo aſſeſſed theſame, into theſaid kynges Exchequer, there to be leuied &amp; paied, by the Collectors of that parties for theſaied reliefes, returned into theſaid Exchequer, to bee therewith charged with the paiment of theſaied Relieffes in ſuche maner, as if theſaid fines had been ſet and Taxed vpon theſaied offendours, for theſaied Reliefes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">IT</hi> is alſo enacted by theſaid aucthoritie of this preſent Parliament that euery of theſaied high Collectours, whiche ſhall accompte for any parte of theſaid Reliefes in the kynges Exchequier, vpon their ſeuerall ſaied accoumptes to bee yelden, ſhalbee allowed yerely duryng theſaied three yeres, for euery pound limited to his Colleccion wherof any ſuche Collectour ſhalbe charged, and yelde accompte, ſixe pence, as parcell of their ſaied charge, that is to ſaie, twoo pence of euery pounde therof<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for ſuche perſones as then haue had the particuler Colleccion, in the Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and other places (as is aforeſaied) ſpecified in his Colleccion: and other twoo pence of euery pounde thereof, euery of theſaied chief Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectours there accomptant, to receiue to their awne vſe for their laboure and charge, in and about the premiſſes: and .ii. d. of euery pound, reſidue to bee deliuered<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> allowed and paied by theſaied Collectours, ſo beeyng thereof allowed, to ſuche of the Commiſſioners as ſhall take vpon them the buſineſſe and laboure, for and aboute the premiſſes: That is to ſaie, euery Collectour to paie that Commiſſioner or Commiſſioners, whiche had the orderyng and the writynges, of and for theſaied Reliefes, where theſaid Collectour or Collectours had their Colleccion, for expences of theſaied Commiſſioners<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo takyng vpon them theſaied buſineſſe, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of their clerkes, writyng theſaied preceptes and eſtreates for the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaied Colleccions, theſame laſt twoo pence of euery pounde, to bee deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded emongeſt theſaied Commiſſioners, hauyng regard to the labor and buſines, taken by them and their ſaied clerkes, in and about the premiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: for whiche parte ſo to theſaied Commiſſioners atteignyng; theſaied Commiſſioners, and euery of them ioyntly and ſeuerally, for his or their ſaied parte<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> maie haue his remedy againſt theſaied Collectour or Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectours, whiche therof been and might haue been allowed, by accion of debt, in whiche the defendaunt ſhal not wage his lawe, neither proteccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or other eſſoyne ſhalbe allowed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">AND</hi> that no perſone now beyng of the nomber of the compaignie,
<pb n="xij" facs="tcp:189036:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> of this preſent Parliament, nor any Commiſſioner ſhalbe named or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to be any Collector, ſubcollector, or preſentor of theſaied reliefes, or of any part therof, nor no Commiſſioner ſhalbe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled, to make any preſentment or certificat, other then in the kynges Exchequer, of for or concerning theſaid reliefes, or any part therof in any of theſaid .iii. yeres And likewiſe that none other perſone, that ſhalbee named or aſſigned to be commiſſioner in any place, to and for thexecucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this act of reliefes in any of theſaid .iii. yeres, be or ſhalbe aſſigned or named hed collector, in any of theſame thre yeres of theſaid reliefes, neither of any part there of. And that euery ſuche perſone or perſones, whiche ſhalbe named and appoyncted (as is aforeſaid) to be hed Collectors, in and for one of the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaied thre yeres, ſhall not be compelled to be Collector, for the other and laſt yere. And theſaied Collectors, whiche ſhalbe aſſigned for the collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of theſaid reliefes, or for any part therof, and euery of them be and ſhalbe acquited and diſcharged, of all maner fees, rewardes, and of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry other charge in the kinges Exchequer or els where, of them or any of theim, by reaſon of that colleccion, paiment or accomptes, or any thyng concernyng theſame to bee aſked. And that if any perſone receiue and take any fees, rewardes or pleaſures of any ſuche accomptant: that then he ſhall forfeit to the kyng, for euery peny or value of a peny ſo taken .xx pence, and ſuffre impriſonment at the kynges pleaſure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">AND</hi> after the taxyng &amp; aſſeſſyng of theſaid yerely reliefes (as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid) had &amp; made, and theſaied eſtreates therof in parchement, vnto the Collectors (in maner &amp; forme before reherſed) deliuered, theſaid Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners whiche ſhall take vpon them the execucion of this act, within the limites of their Commiſſion, by their agrementes ſhall haue metyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges together, at whiche metyng euery of theſaid commiſſioners, whiche then ſhall haue taken vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thexecucion of any part of theſaid com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, ſhall by hymſelf, or by his ſufficient deputie, truely certifie and bryng furth vnto thother commiſſioners, named in theſaid Commiſſion the certificat and preſentment made before hym &amp; ſuche other commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners, as wer limited with him in one limite, ſo that theſame certificates may be acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted and caſt with other certificates, of thother limites with in theſame commiſſion: and then theſaid commiſſioners, and euery nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnto two at the leaſt (as is a foreſaied) if thei be in life, or their executors, or adminiſtrators of their goodes, if thei bee then dedde, ſhall ioyntly &amp; ſeuerally as thei wer deuided within their limites, vnder their ſeales yerely, duryng theſaid .iii. yeres, by their diſcrecio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make one or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall writynges, indented, conteinyng in it aſwell the names of theſaied collectors, by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners for ſuche colleccion, &amp; accompt in thexche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, and paime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in theſaid receipt, deputed &amp; aſſigned, as the groſſe and ſeuerall ſommes, written vnto euery ſuche Collector, to receiue theſaied reliefes, &amp; alſo all fines, amerciamentes &amp; other forfaitures, if any ſuche by reaſon of this act, happen to be within the precinct &amp; limite of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſion,
<pb facs="tcp:189036:13"/> to be certified into the kynges Exchequer by theſaid commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners yerely, duryng theſaid .iii. yeres, before the daies of paiment therof, at theſaied receipt limitted &amp; appoyncted. In whiche writyng or writyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, indented ſo to be certified, ſhalbe plainly declared &amp; expreſſed, aſwel the whole &amp; intier ſomme and ſommes of theſaid relief, ſeuerally limited to the colleccion of theſaied Collectours, as the names of theſaied Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectours, ſeuerally deputed and aſſigned to the Colleccion of theſaied Sommes, ſo that none of theſaied Collectours, ſo certified in theſaied Exchequer, ſhalbee compelled there to accoumpt or to bee charged, but onely to and for the ſommes limited to his Colleccion, and not to or for any ſomme limited to the Colleccion of his felowes, but that euery of theim ſhalbee ſeuerally charged for their partes, limited to their Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leccion. And if theſaied Commiſſioners, ioyned in one commiſſion, emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt theimſelfes, in that matter cannot agree, or if any of theim bee not ready, or refuſe to make certificat with other of theſame Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: that then theſame Commiſſioners maie make ſeuerall Indentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res (in fourme aforeſaid) of their ſeuerall limites or ſeperacions of Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectours, within the limites of their Commiſſion, vpon &amp; in the Hundre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, Wardes, Wapentakes, Lathes, Rapes, or ſuche other like diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, within their ſaid ſeuerall limites of their commiſſion, as the places there ſhall require to bee ſeuered and deuided, and as to theſame Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners ſhall ſeme to make diuiſions, of their limites or Colleccions, for the ſeuerall charges of theſame Collectours, ſo that alway one Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectour ſhalbee charged and accoumpt for his parte to hym to bee limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted onely by hymſelf, and not for any ſomme limited to the parte of any of his felowes. And the charge of euery of the Collectours, to be ſet and certified ſeuerally vpon theim, and euery ſuche Collectoure, vpon his accoumpt and paiment of the ſommes of money, limited within his col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leccion, to bee ſeuerally by hymſelf acquited and diſcharged in theſaied Exchequer, without paiyng any maner of fees or rewardes, to any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone or perſones for theſame, vpon the pein and penaltie laſt aboue ſaid and not to bee charged for any porcion of any other Collectours. And if any Commiſſioner after he hath taken certificat of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that (as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid) ſhall before any ſuche Commiſſioner be examined, and the ſommes rated and ſet, and the bokes and writynges therof, beyng in his handes: or if any Collector or other perſon, charged with any receipt of any part of any of theſaid reliefes, or any other perſon, taxed or otherwiſe, by this act charged, with and for any parcell of theſaid relieffes, or with any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes, for fine, amercement, penaltie, or other forfeiture, happen to dye before ſuche Commiſſioner, Collector, or other, whatſoeuer perſone or perſons haue executed, accompliſhed, ſatiſfied, &amp; ſufficiently diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it, whiche to euery ſuche perſone ſhall appertein or belong to do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to this act: then the Executors and Heires of euery ſuche perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and all other ſeazed of any landes or tenementes, that any ſuche perſon
<pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:189036:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> beeyng charged by this acte and deceaſſyng before he be diſcharged thereof, or any other to his vſe onely had of eſtate of inheritaunce at the tyme that any ſuche perſon was named Commiſſioner, Collectour, or in any otherwiſe charged with &amp; for any maner of thyng to be done, ſatiſfied or payed, by reaſon of this act, and all thoſe that haue in their poſſeſſions or handes any goodes or cattalles, that were to any ſuche perſon at the tyme of his death, landes or tenementes that wer theſame perſones at the tyme that he was (as is aforeſayd) charged by this acte, ſhalbe by theſame compelled and charged to do &amp; accompliſhe in euery caſe as the ſame perſon, ſo beyng charged, ſhould haue done and might haue been compelled to do, if he had been liuyng, after ſuche rate of the landes &amp; goodes of the ſayd Commiſſioner or Collectour, as the partie ſhall haue in his handes. And if theſame Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners for cauſes rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable them mouyng ſhall thynke it not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient, to ioyne in one cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificat, as is before ſayd: then the ſayd perſon or perſones that ſhall firſt ioyne together, or he that ſhal firſt certifie the ſayd writyng indented, as is aforeſayd, ſhal certifie all the names of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners of that Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, wherevpon ſuche writynges ſhalbe there than to be certified, with diuiſions of the hundredes, wapentakes, wardes, tithynges, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places to and among ſuche Commiſſioners, of theſame Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion, with the names of theſame Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners where ſuche ſeperacions &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſions ſhalbe, with the groſſe ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes of money aſwell of &amp; for the ſayd Relief taxed or ſet of or within the ſayd hundredes, wardes, wape<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>takes or other places to him or them deuided or aſſigned that ſhall ſo certifie the ſayd firſt writyng, as of fynes, amerciamentes, penalties, and other forfaitures, if any happen to be within theſame limittes, whereof the ſame writynges ſhalbe certified.</p>
            <p>And after ſuche writyng indented, which (as is aforeſayd) ſhalbe cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefied, and not contayne in it the whole and full ſommes ſet and taxed within the limyttes of theſame Commiſſion, the other Commiſſioners of the ſame, euery of the ſayd thre yeres before the day of paiment of the ſayd Relief at the ſayd receipt limitted and appoincted by this act, ſhal certifie into the ſayd Exchequier by their writyng or writynges inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be made, as is beforeſayd, the groſſe and ſeuerall ſummes ſet and taxed within the places to them limitted for the ſayd ſubſidie and other fynes, amerciamentes, penalties, and forfaytures, with the names of the hundredes, wardes, wape<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>takes, and other places to them aſſigned: or els by their ſayd writynges indented to certifie at the ſayd place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the day of payment therof at the ſayd receipt, as is aforeſayd, reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable cauſes for their excuſes, why they may not make ſuche certificat of and for the ſayd Relief, with fynes, amerciamentes, penalties, and other forfaitures growyng or ſet by reaſon of the cauſes of their lett<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, or of their non certifiyng, as is aboue ſayd, or els in default therof, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to be made out of the Kynges Exchequier againſt the ſayd Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners
<pb facs="tcp:189036:14"/> and euery of theim not makyng certificat, as is aforeſayd, by the diſcrecion of the Theſaurour &amp; Barons of the ſayd Exchequier.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes that if any perſon or perſones chargeable to this Relief of payment for his goodes ſhal happen at any tyme duryng the ſayd thre yeres to be ſet or preſented in two or mo places then one, and the ſame beyng certified into the kynges court of Exchequier, that then the partie or parties ſo ſet or preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted &amp; certified takyng a corporal other before the Barons of the kynges Exchequier, or before any two of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or before any perſon or perſones beyng aucthoriſed by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion to be directed from the ſayd Barons or any of theim, whiche commiſſion or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſions the ſayd Barons or ii. of them ſhalbe authoriſed &amp; haue full power &amp; aucthoritie to make by this act, that he or they is or be the ſame ſelfe perſon or perſons ſo ſet, and that he or they is or be, ſet or preſented in two or mo places then one. And that he or they haue then been by the ſpace of one yere nexte before the takyng of the ſayd othe more conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt and dwellyng in any one of the ſame places where he or they ſhal ſo happen to be ſet or preſented then in the other: that then the partie of parties ſo ſet or preſented in two or mo places then one, and ſo takyng his othe without any other plee in writyng, ſhalbe clerely diſcharged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the kyng, his heyres &amp; ſucceſſours or euery of the ſayd aſſeſemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and preſentmentes, ſauyng onely of the aſſeſement and preſentment in the place where he or they was or were moſte conuerſaunt &amp; dwellyng as is before ſayd.</p>
            <p>And be it alſo enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayd, that the Barons of the kynges Exchequer or two of theim for the tyme beyng, ſhal not onely haue full power &amp; aucthoritie to receiue and take the othe of ſuche partie or parties as ſhalbe ſo ſet or preſented in any mo places then one, but ſhall alſo vpon the ſame othe or othes ſo taken, diſcharge the partie &amp; parties of all ſuche ſummes of money as he or they ſhould bee in any wiſe charged with, ſauyng onely of ſuche ſummes of money as the ſame partie or parties were ſo ſeſſed at in ſuche place and places where he or they were moſt conuerſaunt and dwellyng as is aforeſayd.</p>
            <p>And to the intent the kynges maieſtie may be truly &amp; iuſtly anſwered of the ſayd relief of the polle of ſhepe before by vs grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to his high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: be it ordained and enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayd, that yerely duryng theſayd iii. yeres before the firſt day of May, there ſhalbe a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion with ten cedules containyng in them the tenor of this acte to be annexed to ſuche commiſſion directed vnder the kynges great ſeale of England into euery cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie, ſhyre, ridyng, citie, borough, toune corporat, and the Iſle of Wight, and into all and euery other place within this realme and other the kynges dominions that is or ſhalbe chargeable to the paiment of the ſayd Relief of the polle of ſhepe to ſuche perſones as the ſame yere before were Commiſſioners for the aſſeſement and taxacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the value of euery perſons goodes and ſubſtaunce, in the ſame ſhire
<pb n="xiiii" facs="tcp:189036:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> or other place, or to as many of them as ſhalbe then liuyng, and to ſuche other perſones as the ſayd lorde Chauncelor and other with him before named ſhall name and appoinct. By the whiche commiſſion the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners ſhal haue full power and aucthoritie to enquire by the othes of the Perſon, Vicar or curate, &amp; iiii. or as many honeſt perſons of euery pariſh, village, and hamlet within the limittes of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Conſtable, Tithyngman or Borſolder ſhalbe one, if any Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Tithyngman or Borſolder be dwellyng in the ſame pariſhe, village or Hamlet, and by the othes of as many other honeſt &amp; diſcrete perſons as they ſhall thynke co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient, or otherwiſe by ſuche meanes and polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies as they ſhal thynke beſt, wherby the truth may appeare of the nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and natures of all and ſynguler ſheepe beyng within the limittes of their commiſſion, whoſe they be, in what toune or pariſh the owner dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, and of what ſtate or degree he is, and whether for the moſte part of the yere they be kept in ſeuerall paſtures, or ſeuerall marſhes, or in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, or groundes commonly vſed to be tylled: the tenor of whiche othe hereafter foloweth.</p>
            <p>¶ Ye ſhall diligently enquire and iuſtly and truly preſent and certifie vs the kynges Commſſioners what nomber of Ewes, Wethers &amp; other ſhere ſhepe be within the limittes of your charge, whoſe they be, in what toune or pariſhe the owner dwelleth, of what condicion and degre he is, &amp; whether for the moſte part of the yere they be kept in ſeuerall paſtures or ſeueral Marſhes, or in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons or grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des comenly vſed to be tylled, as ye truſt to be ſaued by the merites of Chriſtes paſſion.</p>
            <p>And it is alſo ordained and enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayd, that yerely duryng the ſayd thre yeres, on the Tueſdaye after the feaſt of the Natiuitie of ſainct Ihon Baptiſt, there ſhalbe a generall ſuruay made, of all and ſinguler ſhepe, in euery pariſh, village and other place within this realme, the Iſle of Wight &amp; other the kynges dominions chargea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the payment of this Relief of ſheepe, by ſuche perſones as ſhalbe appointed &amp; ſworne to do the ſame in maner and fourme before reherſed. And that vpon ſuche ſuruay, euery ſhepe ſhalbe taken for a ſhere ſhepe that is at the tyme of the ſuruay of the age of one yere or more, albeit the ſame ſhepe be not at that tyme ſhorne.</p>
            <p>And it is further ordained and enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayd, that if any parſon to the intent to defraude the execucion of this ſtatute ſhall remoue the ſayd daye of ſuruay his ſheepe before the ſuruay taken from the vſual place where thei were comonly kept for the moſte part of the yere, or els ſhall cauſe them or any part of them to be conueyed to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other place whereby they ſhall not be ſuruayed, or whereby the kyng ſhall loſe any part of the Relief to him geuen by this ſtatute, that euery perſon ſo offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng ſhall forfaite and loſe to the kynges Maieſtie, treble ſo muche as he ought to pay by vertue of this ſtatute.</p>
            <p>And it is alſo ordayned &amp; enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayd, that if any perſon ſommoned to appeare before the ſayd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners, do make
<pb facs="tcp:189036:15"/> defaulte hauyng no reaſonable excuſe: or appearyng, ſhal refuſe to take the ſayd othe, or takyng the ſayd othe ſhal not diligently attend and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour the execucion therof, or ſhall not appeare and make preſentment before the ſayd Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners at ſuche tyme &amp; place as he ſhalbe appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that euery perſon ſo offendyng for euery ſuche default ſhal forfayte and loſe to the kynges Maieſtie xl. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>And it is alſo ordayned and enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayd, that yerely duryng the ſayd thre yeres within one moneth next after the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uay of ſhepe, and the preſentmentes made by the viewers of the ſheepe in maner and forme as is before declared, the Commiſſioners in euery ſhire or other place ſhal all or the moſt part aſſemble them ſelues toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and conferre the preſentme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes made before them of the ſhepe, with the preſentmentes before made of the value of the goodes &amp; ſubſtaunce of all perſones within the limittes of their commiſſion. And that vpon ſuche collacions of the preſentmentes if it ſhal appeare vnto them that any perſon is chargeable by vertue of this acte to paye for the polle of his ſhepe whiche before was not charged for his goodes. Or that if any perſon within the limittes of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion be chargeable to pay more after the rate of the polle of his ſhepe preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted before them, then he was before for the value of his ſubſtaunce of his goodes, the ſaid Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners or the more part of them as they ſhalbe deuided, ſhall within one moneth next after ſuche aſſemble by their writynges indented to be ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſealed by them, make furth extreates of all &amp; ſinguler ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes of money that any perſon ought to paye for the rate of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> polle of his ſhepe not beeyng before charged with his goodes, or for the ouerplus that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſon ought to pay for that the rate of the polle of his ſheepe doeth ſurmount the paiment before made of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> value of his goodes, &amp; theſame writynges ſhal not onely deliuer vnto ſufficient and ſubſtanciall inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitantes, Conſtables, Subconſtables and other officers and perſones ioyntely of hundredes, tounes, pariſhes, and other places within the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittes where the owners dwel or haue their moſte vſual abidyng, to be leuied, gathered, and receiued of the owner of ſuche ſheepe or his execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours or adminiſtratours, but alſo ſhall in like maner deliuer the like writyng to the high Collectour of the ſame limit, to charge him with the receipt therof of the Subcollectour or Subcollectours, &amp; the payment therof at the kynges receipte. And that the ſayd Subcollectours, and Commiſſioners, ſhall not onely haue for their labours vi. d. of euery pound, commyng, growyng and to bee payed to the kynges Maieſtie for the Relief of the polle of the ſheepe by vertue of this acte, but alſo that they and euery of them ſhall haue the like power and auctoritie to gather and leuy theſame, and all fynes and forfaytures commyng and growyng for the execucion and gatheryng of this Relief of the polle of ſhepe by ſuche like waies and meanes as before in this act be limitted &amp; appointed for the leuiyng and gatheryng of the Relief of goodes. And that the ſayd Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners, Collectours and all and euery other perſon
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:189036:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> and perſons ſhall behaue, ordre, and vſe themſelues in all &amp; euery thyng concernyng thexecucion of this part of the ſtatute touchyng the leuiyng and gatheryng of the relief of the polle of the ſhepe, as before in this act is limitted &amp; appointed for to do touching the Relief of the goodes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> like paynes, penalties &amp; forfaitures as be before declared in this acte.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes and be it ordained and enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayd that al &amp; ſinguler ſummes of money due to the kynges Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of this Relief of the polle of ſhepe, ſhalbe gathered by the Subcol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectour or high collectour of the limittes where the owner dwelleth and none other place.</p>
            <p>And it is further ordayned and enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayd, that the ſayd Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners for the ſuruay of the nombre and value of the ſhepe ſhal yerely duryng theſayd thre yeres make returne and certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficat vnto the kynges Exchequier before the x. day of October aſwel of the count<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> parte of al and euery extreates deliuered by them to the high Collectours, as alſo of all and ſinguler preſentmentes made before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and of all &amp; ſinguler their procedynges concernyng the ſayd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion. And that in the ende of all and euery their certificats they ſhall make ſpecial remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces and declaracions of all and ſinguler perſons not dwellyng within the limittes of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion, that haue ſheepe within the limittes of theſame commiſſion, where ſuche perſons dwel, &amp; of what ſtate and degree they be, what nombre, and what kynde of ſhepe they be, and in what grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des for the moſt part of the yere they be kept. And that vpon ſuche returne and certificat of the commiſſion to be made by the Commiſſioners for the ſuruay of ſhepe beyng conferred with the bokes of the taxation and value of the ſubſtaunce or euery perſon, if it ſhal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare that the kynges Maieſtie ought to haue more by any meanes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the ſayd Relief then before was payed or payable, that then vpon an extreate therof to be made out of the ſayd court of the Exchequier to the high collectour of the place where the partie that ought to pay more dwelleth, theſame Collectour ſhalbe therwith charged, &amp; ſhall gather &amp; leuy theſame in like maner and fourme as he ought to do the reſt of his Collections.</p>
            <p>And to thintent the kynges Maieſtie may be iuſtly anſwered for the Relief by vs before graunted of the price and value of all clothes: be it ordayned and enacted, that the Commiſſioners to be appointed for the taxacion of the Relief of the ſubſtaunce of euery perſon, ſhall haue full power and aucthoritie by vertue of this acte, and of their commiſſion, as they ſhalbe deuided, to name, conſtitute, and appoint, in euery Citie, Borough, Toune, Hundred and pariſhe, within the limittes of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſions by their diſcrecions, ſuche and ſo many honeſt, ſubſtancial, and diſcrete menne, to be praiſers of the ſayd clothes, chargeable to the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:189036:16"/> of this Relief of clothes, as they ſhall thinke conuenient &amp; neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, &amp; them from tyme to tyme to alter &amp; put newe in their places as they ſhall haue occaſion. And that theſayd prayſers before they take vpon them the appraiſement of ſuche clothes, ſhalbe ſworne in maner &amp; forme folowyng.</p>
            <p>¶ Ye ſhal faythfully and truely eſteme and ſet the iuſt pryce &amp; value of all ſuche clothes as ſhalbe brought vnto you to be viewed and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as ye ſhal in your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences thynke theſame worth to be ſolde when they ſhalbe wrought, and theſame ſhall not ſuffer to be deliuered out of your cuſtody, tyl ye haue made of the colour, kynde and pryce therof an entry both in the boke of the clothier and alſo of the Aulnageour or his deputie, &amp; ſet to your handes or markes declaryng who was the owner of the clothe, and the kind and price therof, ſo helpe you God and by this booke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">AND</hi> it is alſo ordayned and enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayd, that all kynde of clothes whiche from and after the feaſt of the Natiuitie of ſainct Ihon Baptiſt next commyng, duryng the ſpace of thre yeres then folowyng, ſhalbe made within this realme, or Wales, to be vttered and put to ſale, ſhalbe ſealed with the kynges ſeale, remainyng in the cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Aulnageour, or his deputie, or deputies, and praiſed by two of the ſayd praiſers at the leaſt, and entred into the bokes hereafter in this act mencioned, vpon paine of forfayture of the ſame clothe, the one halfe to the kynges Maieſtie, the other to the partie that ſhall ſeaze the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">AND</hi> it is alſo enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayd, that there ſhalbe it. bookes yerely made, of the appraiſyng of all and euery kynde of clothe to be made duryng the ſayd .iii. yeres, thone of which bokes to remaine with the Aulnageour or his deputie, wherin ſhalbe written the colour, kynde and price of all and ſynguler clothes viewed and apprayſed that yere, accordyng to the tenor of this ſtatute, vnto whiche boke, the owner of euery cloth or ſome other perſon for him, and the praiſours, ſhal ſet to their handes or markes when the clothe is ſealed: And the other booke ſhal remayne with the owner of the ſayd clothe whervnto the ſayd Aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nageour and prayſours ſhal ſet their handes and markes. And that the owner of all and euery cloth chargeable to the payment of the Relief of clothes graunted by this acte, yerely within xx. dayes after the yere ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired, ſhal deliuer his ſayd booke ſo ſubſcribed or marked with the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the Aulnageour or his deputie and prayſours to the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners for the taxacion and aſſeſment of the ſayd Relief within the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte where ſuche clothier dwelleth, or to one of them, vpon payn of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayture by the ſame clothier of treble ſo muche as he ought to pay to the kyng by reaſon of the aforeſayd Relief of his clothes ſo ſealed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">AND</hi> it is further ordayned and enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayd,
<pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:189036:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> that euery Aulnageour ſhall yerely fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; after the ſayd feaſt of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titutie of ſaint Ihon Baptiſt next commyng, kepe a parſite booke of the colour, kynd, and price of all and ſinguler clothes by him ſealed, and the names of the owners therof in maner and fourme as is before declared, and theſame booke yerely ſhal make and deliuer to the Commiſſioners, for the taxacion of goodes within the limites wher ſuche Clothe maker dwelleth, or to one of them, within xx. dayes next after the yere expired.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">AND</hi> it is further ordayned and enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayd, that if any Aulnageour or his deputie do not make and deliuer theſayd booke in maner and forme before reherſed, or do wylfully conceale any clothe by him ſealed, &amp; do not entre it into the ſayd booke, that for ſuche offence the ſayd Aulnageour ſhal not onely forfayte his office, but alſo ſhal make fyne at the kynges will.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">AND</hi> it is alſo ordayned and enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayd, that the ſayd Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners of that limitte hauyng receiued the ſayd bookes of the Aulnageour or his deputie or deputies, and the owner of the clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, ſhal conferre the rates of the Relief of the clothes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> comprehended in the ſayd bookes, with the taxacion and payment of the owner of the ſame clothes for his goodes. So that if it ſhal appeare thereby to them that the owner of any cloth is chargeable to pay for his clothes, whiche before was not chargeable for his goodes, or that ſuche owner ought to paye more after the rate of the Relief of his clothes containyng in the bookes deliuered to theim, then he was before charged for the value of his ſubſtaunce of his goodes, the ſayd Commiſſioners as they be deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſhal within one moneth next after the ſayd bookes receiued, by their writyng indented to be ſigned and ſealed by them, make furth extreates of al &amp; ſinguler ſummes of money that any perſon ought to pay for his clothes, not beeyng before charged with his goodes &amp; for the ouerplus that any ſuche perſon ought to pay for that the rate of the clothes doeth ſurmount the payment of the value of his goodes before made: and the ſame writyng ſhal deliuer to the high Collectour of theſame limitte, to charge him with the receipt hereof, of the maker of the ſayd clothes: and the payment therof at the kynges receipte. And that the ſayd high Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectour ſhal haue the like power &amp; aucthoritie to gather &amp; leuy theſame, by ſuche like wayes and meanes as before in this acte bee limitted and appointed to the Subcollectour for the leuiyng and gatheryng of the Relief of goodes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">AND</hi> it is further ordayned and enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayd, that the ſayd Commiſſioners ſhall yerely duryng the ſayd thre yeres make returne and certificat into the kinges Exchequier before the tenth daye of October, not only of the counterpane of all and euery extreate
<pb facs="tcp:189036:17"/> deliuered by him to the high Collectour, but alſo of the booke receiued of the Aulnageour as is aforeſayd, and the praiſours names, and of all and ſinguler their procedynges co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceruyng the ſayd payment of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of clothes.</p>
            <p>And it is further ordayned and enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayd, that euery of the ſayd high Collectours whiche ſhall accompt for any part of the ſayd Relief of clothes in the kynges Exchequier, vpon their ſeuerall ſayd acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptes to be yelden, ſhalbe alowed yerely duryng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd thre yeres, for euery pound limitted to his Collection, wherof any ſuche Collectour ſhalbe charged and yelde accompte, vi. d. as parcell of their ſayd charge, that is to ſay, ii. d. of euery pound thereof for ſuche perſons as bee limitted to be prayſours, for their paynes and labours: and other ii. d. of euery pound therof, euery of the ſayd chiefe Collectours there ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comptant, to receiue to their owne vſe for their labours and charge in &amp; aboute the premiſſes: and ii. d. of euery pounde reſidue to be deliuered, allowed and payed by the ſayd Collectours, ſo beeyng thereof allowed, to ſuche of the Commiſſioners as ſhal take vpon theim the buſynes and labour for &amp; about the premiſſes, that is to ſay, euery Collectour to pay that Commiſſioner or Commiſſioners whiche had the orderyng and the writynges of and for the ſayd Relief of clothes where the ſayd Collector or Collectours had their colleccion, for expences of the ſayd Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſo takyng vpon them the ſayd buſynes and labour of their clerkes writyng the ſayd preceptes and eſtretes for the ſayd colleccions: the ſame laſt ii. d. of euery pound to bee deuided among the ſayd Commiſſioners, hauyng regard to the labour and buſynes taken by them and their ſayd clearkes in and aboute the premiſſes. For whiche parte ſo to the ſayd commiſſioners attainyng, the ſayd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners vi. v. iiii. iii. or as many of them as ſhalbe therto appointed by the kynges commiſſion and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them ioyntly and ſeuerally for his or their ſayd part may haue his remedy againſt the ſayd Collectour or Collectours whiche thereof been and might haue been allowed by accion of debt, in whiche the defendant ſhall not wage his lawe, neither proteccion, Iniunccion or other eſſoyne ſhalbe allowed.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, that this graunt of Relief nor any other thyng therin contayned, do in any wyſe extend to charge the inhabitauntes or dwellers within Ireland, Bulleyne and the countie of theſame, Calleys, Hammes, Guyſnes and the Marches of theſame, Ierneſey and Garne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey or any of them, of for or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyng any goodes whiche the ſaid inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitauntes or dwellers, or any other to their vſe haue within Irelande, Bulleyne, the countie of the ſame, Calleys, Hammes, Guyſnes, or other Marches of theſame, Ierneſey, Garneſey, ar in any of them.</p>
            <p>Prouided alſo, that the ſayd graunt of Relief do not in any maner of wiſe extend or be preiudicial or hurtful to thinhabitau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes or reſiauntes
<pb n="xvii" facs="tcp:189036:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> at this preſent tyme within the fiue Portes corporate, or to any of their membres incorporate or vnited to the ſame fiue Portes, or to any of the ſame fiue Portes, of or for any part or parcel of the ſayd ſummes grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in this preſent Parliament of the ſayd inhabitauntes now reſiau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes or any of them to bee taxed, ſet, aſked, leuied or payed, but that the ſayd inhabitauntes and now reſiauntes of the ſayd Portes &amp; their membres and euery of them, bee and ſhalbe of and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſayd graunt &amp; payment of the ſayd Relief of their goodes and cattalles duryng their reſiauncie there and no lenger acquited and diſcharged, any matter or whatſoeuer thyng in this preſent acte made or had to the contrary notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided alſo that this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t act of Relief, ne any other thing therin co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayned extend to any of the Engliſh inhabitau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes or reſiau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes in any of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ties of Northu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>berland, Cumberla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, Weſtmerland, the toune of Barwyke, the toune of Newcaſtle vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Tyne and the biſhopricke of Durham, nor to any of them, of for or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyng any goodes, clothes or ſhcepe, whiche the ſame inhabitauntes or dwellers or any other to their vſe, haue within the ſayd counties of Northumberland, Cumberland, and Weſtmerla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or the toune of Barwike, the toune of Newcaſtle vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Tyne, or the biſhopricke of Durham or any of theim, but that they and euery of them, ſhalbe of &amp; from the ſayd Relief, of and for their goodes, liyng and beyng in the ſame cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ties, tounes &amp; biſhopricke or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vtterly acquited and diſcharged, any thing in this preſent act before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſed to the contrary notwithſtandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided alſo that this act ne any thyng therein contained ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to the goodes of any College, Hall, or Oſtle within the vniuerſities of Oxford &amp; Cambryge or any of them, or to the goodes of the College of Wynton. founded by biſhop Wykham, or to the goodes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> College of Eton next Wyndeſore, or to the goodes of any reader or ſcholer with in the ſayd Vniuerſities and Colleges, or any of them there remainyng for ſtudye, without fraude or couyn, any thyng in this act contayned to the contrary in any wyſe notwithſtandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes and be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayd that no ſpiritual perſon ſhalbe charged by this act for any of his goodes or cattalles, other then for ſheepe, nor ſhalbe charged by this acte for any ſuche his ſhepe whiche he hath, or at any tyme within thre yeres next fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowyng ſhal haue or kepe for the only purpoſe to be ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or eaten in his houſe, ſo as the nombre of the ſame ſhepe ſo purpoſed to be ſpent &amp; eaten yerely in his ſayd houſe, do not excede the nombre of foure hundreth ſhepe for one yere, nor for any ſuche his ſhepe as do go and fede, or ſhall go or feede for the moſt part of euery yere of iii. yeres next co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his landes, tenementes or conunons, whereof ſuche ſpiritual perſone is or ſhalbe ſeazed in the right of his churche or promocion ſpiritual, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, tenementes or commons be chargeable to the payment of the firſt fruites and tentes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:189036:18"/>
            <p>And foraſmuche as diuers and ſondry the kynges Maieſties tenaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and other thinhabitauntes and dwellers within the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ties of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broke, Carmarthen, Cardygan, Glamorgan, Breknock, Radnor, Mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gomery, Denbigh, Flynt, Marioneth, Angleſey, Carneruon and of the countie Palentine of Cheſter, be at this preſent tyme charged &amp; charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with the ſeuerall paymentes of diuers great ſummes of money (by the name of a Myſc) due to his Maieſtie, according to the ſeueral cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of the ſayd cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tres, for the payment wherof diuers and ſondry the gentlemen and other the inhabitantes of the ſayd counties be and ſtand bound to his highnes: The kyng our ſoueraigne lorde is therfore plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and contented that it be prouided, ordained &amp; enacted by the auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie aforeſayd, that this act or any thing therin co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained, ſhal not extend to charge any of the kynges Maieſties tenauntes &amp; other thinhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes and dwellers within any of the ſayd cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ties of Penbroke, Carmarthen, Cardygan, Glamorgan, Brecknock, Radnor, Mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tgomery, Denbigh, Flynt, Marioneth, Angleſey, Carnaruon and the countie Palentine of Cheſter beyng charged or chargeable with the ſayd Myſe for or with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the paymentes of the ſayd Relief grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinges Maieſtie by this acte, vntill the ſeuerall dayes and tymes appointed and agreed for the paimentes of the ſayd Myſes ſhalbe expired. And that the firſt pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſayd relief for goodes ſhalbe made at the receipt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinges Exchequier before the firſt day of Maye then nexte folowyng after the day appointed for the later payment to bee made of the ſayd Myſe, and ſo yerely before the firſt day of May at the receipt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Exchequer vntil the thre ſeueral payme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of the ſayd Relief be fully made in ſuche and like maner, forme and ordre as is ordayned and appointed by this act for the kynges ſubiectes concernyng the ſayd Relief of goodes to be made at the receipt of the ſayd Exchequer, accordyng to the tenor of this preſent act. And alſo that the fyrſt paymentes of Relief for clothes and ſhepe in euery of the ſayd ſeueral Counties ſhalbe made in the ſayd Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer after the ſayd Miſes, due to bee payde, at ſuche and like dayes &amp; tymes yetely as is afore limited by this acte: this act or any thing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contayned to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtandyng.</p>
            <p>And furthermore, be it enacted by aucthoritie aforeſayd that the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauntes and dwellers of euery of the ſayd counties in this prouiſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, ſhall ſeuerally before the feaſt of ſainct Martyne the biſhop next enſuyng, certifie in the kynges ſayd Court of Exchequer vnder the ſeale of two Iuſtices of peace of euery of the ſayd counties, whereof one to be of the Quorum, when and as what day the laſt payment of the ſayd ſeueral Myſes in euery of the ſayd counties ſhal ende and expire.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div rend="italic" type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted in the houſe of Richard Grafton, printer to the Kynges Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:189036:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:189036:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:189036:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
